本字幕由YYeTs人人影视修正制作
仅供学习 禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
最新最快的HR-HDTV 请登陆 www.YYeTs.net
字幕： 小瑞  后期： lisi31415926
■
欢迎有能力的影视爱好者加入我们字幕组
加入仅凭个人兴趣爱好 没有任何金钱实质回报
西贡
Saigon.
妈的
Shit.
我还是在西贡
I'm still only in Saigon.
每次醒来  总以为重返森林
Every time, I think I'm gonna wake up back in thejungle.
我第一次回家时  情况最糟
When I was home after my first tour, it was worse.
醒来后  发觉只是噩梦一场
I'd wake up, and there'd be nothing.
我几乎没和妻子说话
I hardly said a word to my wife
直到答应离婚才说了个  是
until I said yes to a divorce.
当我在战场时  很想回家
When I was here, I wanted to be there.
当我在家
When I was there,
又想着回到森林
all I could think of was getting backinto thejungle.
我已回来一星期了
I'm here a weeknow.
等待任务
Waiting for a mission...
意志消沉
getting softer.
我留在房间越久  只会越软弱
Every minute I stay in this room, I get weaker.
越共留在森林越久
And every minute Charlie squats in the bush,
就越强悍
he gets stronger.
每次环顾四周
Each time I looked around,
墙壁似乎分秒迫近
the walls moved in a little tighter.
每个人都有愿望
Everyone gets everything he wants.
我渴望任务
I wanted a mission...
真是咎由自取  他们给了我一个
and for my sins, they gave me one.
像客房服务般交给了我
Brought it up to me like room service.
威尔德上尉  你在吗？
Captain Willard? Are you in there?
在！ 我就来
Yeah, I'm comin'.
这真是项艰巨的任务
It was a real choice mission.
当完成它后
And when it was over,
我绝不想再有第二个
I'd never want another.
有何贵干？
What do you want?
你没事吧  上尉
Are you all right, Captain?
我像有事吗？
What does it look like?
-你是威尔德上尉吗？ 505营？  -没错
-Are you Willard, 505th Battalion?  -AffiIrmative.
-第173空降部队？  -是的
-1 73rd Airborne?  -Yeah.
-隶属特种部队？  -把门关上！
-Assigned to SOG?  -Hey, buddy, gonna shut the door?
我们奉命送你去机场
We have orders to escort you to the airfiIeld.
什么罪名？
What are the charges?
-我犯了什么事？  -你没犯事  上尉
-What'd I do?  -There's no charges, Captain.
让你向老川的情报处报到
You have orders to report to Com-Sec Intelligence at Nha Trang.
－你看  －没错吧！
-I see.  -All right?
-派我去老川？  -是的
-Nha Trang, for me?  -That's right.
上尉  你有几个小时收拾行李
Come on, Captain. You still have a few hours to get cleaned up.
-我不太舒服  -上尉？
-I'm not feeling too good.  -Captain?
戴夫  过来帮把手  他烂醉如泥
Dave, come here and give me a hand. We got a dead one.
来吧  上尉  冲个凉
Come on, Captain. Let's take a shower.
-别乱来  -扶稳他
-Don't be an ass.  -Get a hold of him good.
我们帮你冲凉  上尉
We're gonna take a shower, Captain. In we go.
站在这下面  上尉
Stand underneath this, Captain.
我要去世上最凶险的地方
I was going to the worst place in the world...
当时却一无所知
and I didn't even know it yet.
花数星期  逆流而上数百公里
Weeks away and hundreds of miles up a river...
在战火中迂回前行  就像一条主电缆
that snaked through the war like a main circuit cable...
直插向库尔兹
plugged straight into kurtz.
上校的回忆录传到我手上
It was no accident that I got to be the caretaker...
绝非偶然
of Colonel Walter E. kurtz's memory--
正如我回到西贡一样
any more than being back in Saigon was an accident.
他的故事  有一部份关于我
There is no way to tell his story without telling my own.
若他的故事是真实告白
If his story is really a confession--
威尔德上尉报到  长官
Captain Willard reporting, sir.
我的也是
then so is mine.
-上尉  很好  进来吧  -谢谢  长官
-Captain. Good. Come on in.  -Thank you, sir.
稍息
Stand at ease.
将军
General.
抽烟吗？
You want a cigarette?
不了  谢谢  长官
No, thank you, sir.
上尉  你以前见过这位先生吗？
Have you ever seen this man before?
-没有  -见过将军或我吗？
-No, sir.  -Met the general or myself?
从未私下会面  长官
No, sir.Not personally.
你经常单独行动  是吗？
You've worked a lot on your own?
是的  长官
Yes, sir, I have.
报告上说你擅长  情报工作和反间谍
Your report specifiIes intelligence...
替情报一处工作
counterintelligence with Com-Sec, ''I'' Corps.
我不能透露行动内容
I'm not presently disposed to discuss those operations, sir.
你在情报一处  不是为中情局效力吗？
Did you not work for the CIA in ''I'' Corps?
不是  长官
No, sir.
你没于1968年6月18日
Did you not assassinate a government tax collector...
在广储县暗杀政府税务人员吗？
Quang Tri Province, June 1 8, 1 968?
上尉？
Captain?
长官  我不知道任何类似事件或行动
Sir, I am unaware of any such activity or operation--
就算知道  也不能透露
nor would I be disposed to discuss such an operation...
有关行动的一切  长官
if it did, in fact, exist, sir.
我们边吃边谈吧
I thought we'd have a bite of lunch while we talk.
希望你胃口好  上尉
I hope you brought a good appetite, Captain.
我注意到  你一只手不方便
I notice that you have a bad hand there.
受伤了？
You wounded?
休假时钓鱼弄伤的  长官
I had a little fiIshing accident on R and R, sir.
-休假时去钓鱼？  -是的  长官
-Fishing on R and R?  -Yes, sir.
身体好了吗？  准备好执行任务了？
But you're feeling fiIt? You're ready for duty?
是的  将军  准备好了
Yes, General. Very much so, sir.
看看有什么  烧牛肉
Well, let's see what we have here, roast beef,
通常还不错
and usually it's not bad.
吃吃看  杰瑞  传一下
Try some,Jerry, and pass it around.
两边一起传  省点时间
To save a little time, we might pass both ways.
上尉  吃这虾吗？
Captain, I don't know how you feel about this shrimp...
若你吃下
but if you'll eat it
足见你胆识过人
you'll never have to prove your courage in any other way.
我也要一块
I swear, why don't I just take a piece here?
上尉  你听说过沃特库尔兹上校吗？
Captain, you've heard of Colonel Walter E. kurtz?
是的  我听过这名字
Yes, sir, I've heard the name.
天呀！
Oh,Jesus!
第五特种部队作战指挥
Operations offiIcer, Fifth Special Forces.
卢克  放录音带给上尉听
Luke, would you play that tape for the captain, please?
-好的  长官  -仔细听  上尉
-Yes, sir. I'm sorry, sir.  -Listen to this carefully, Captain.
10月9日  4：30  防区彼得  域陀  阿甘
October 6, 0430 hours, sector Peter, Victor, king.
在柬埔寨监听到的
These were monitored out of Cambodia.
证实是库上校的声音
This has been verifiIed as Col. kurtz's voice.
我看见一只蜗牛
I watched a snail...
爬在剃刀边缘
crawl along the edge of a straight razor.
这是我的梦
That's my dream.
噩梦
That's my nightmare.
爬动  滑行
Crawling, slithering...
在剃刀
along the edge...
边缘
of a straight razor...
活生生的
and surviving.
接收编号11  68年12月30日  5时
Transmission 1 1, received '68, December 30, 0500 hours.
防区阿甘  祖路  阿甘
Sector king, Zulu, king.
但我们必须杀死它们
But we must kill them.
把它们烧成灰
We must incinerate them.
一只接一只的猪
Pig after pig.
一只接一只的牛
Cow after cow.
一个接一个的村庄  一支接一支的军队
Village after village. Army after army.
他们称我是杀手
And they call me an assassin.
真是五十步笑百步
What do you call it when the assassins accuse the assassin?
他们说谎
They lie.
他们说谎  而我们对说谎者
They lie, and we have to be merciful...
还得仁慈
for those who lie.
那些个富豪
Those nabobs.
我讨厌他们
I hate them.
我很讨厌他们
I do hate them.
沃特库尔兹  是本国培育出的
Walt kurtz was one of the most outstanding offiIcers...
最优秀的军官之一
this country's ever produced.
在各方面都出类拔萃
He was brilliant. He was outstanding in every way.
人品也很好  有人道精神
And he was a good man, too, a humanitarian man.
聪明  幽默
A man of wit and humor.
他加入了特种部队
He joined the Special Forces.
此后
And after that his...
他的想法  行事
ideas, methods...
变得
became...
反常
unsound.
Unsound.
现在  他率领越南山民军
Now he's crossed into Cambodia with this...
越境进入柬埔寨  他们敬他若神明
Montagnard army of his that worship the man like a god...
连极荒谬的命令也奉行
and follow every order, however ridiculous.
我还有更惊人的消息要告诉你
Well, I have some other shocking news to tell you.
库上校将因谋杀
Col. kurtz was about to be arrested
而被捕
for murder.
我不明白  长官  他杀了谁？
I don't follow, sir. Murdered who?
库尔兹下令处决了  几名越南情报员
kurtz had ordered the execution of some Vietnamese intelligence agents--
认为他们是双重间谍
men he believed were double agents.
他独断专行
So he took matters into his own hands.
你瞧  威尔德
Well, you see, Willard...
这场战役
in this war,
是非难辨
things get confused out there.
包括权力  理想  旧道德观
Power, ideals, the old morality...
以及实际的军事需要
and practical military necessity.
但在那和当地人一起
But out there with these natives...
被敬为神明
it must be a temptation to...
很是诱人
be God.
因为任何人的心中  必有冲突
Because there's a conflict in every human heart...
在理性和非理性间
between the rational and the irrational...
善与恶间
between good and evil...
善不一定总战胜恶
and good does not always triumph.
有时
Sometimes...
林肯说的  善良天使
the dark side...
会被邪恶击败
overcomes what Lincoln called the better angels of our nature.
每个人都有临界点
Every man has got a breaking point.
你和我也一样
You and I have them.
库尔兹已到了他的
Walt kurtz has reached his.
很明显  他已疯了
And very obviously, he has gone insane.
没错  长官  显然是疯了
Yes, sir. Very much so, sir. Obviously insane.
你的任务是乘海军巡逻艇  沿着湄南河
Your mission is to proceed up the Nung River in a navy patrol boat--
找寻库上校的踪迹
pick up Col. kurtz's path at Nu Mung Ba...
跟着它  沿路收集情报
follow it, learn what you can along the way.
当你发现上校  用一切手段
When you fiInd the colonel, infiIltrate his team by--
渗入他的组织
whatever means available
终结上校的指挥
and terminate the colonel's command.
处决上校
Terminate the colonel?
他在那里为所欲为
He's out there operating without any decent restraint...
做出不可饶恕的
totally beyond the pale of any acceptable...
行径
human conduct...
而他仍握有军权
and he is still on the fiIeld, commanding troops.
执行军纪  处决他
Terminate with extreme prejudice.
要明白  上尉  这任务从不存在
You understand, Captain, that this mission...
也不会记录在案
does not exist nor will it ever exist.
我杀过多少人？
How many people had I already killed?
我能肯定的有6个
There were those six that I knew about for sure--
他们都死在我跟前
close enough to blow their last breath in my face.
但这次我要杀同胞
But this time it was an American...
而且是个军官
and an officer.
对我来说  应该没什么分别
That wasn't supposed to make any difference to me...
事实上却不好受
but it did.
妈的
Shit.
在战场上指控人谋杀
Charging a man with murder in this place...
就像在  印第500车上  开超速罚单
was like handing out speeding tickets at the Indy 500.
我接受了任务
I took the mission.
我还能怎么办？
What the hell else was I gonna do?
但我真的不知道  找到了他会怎样做
But I really didn't know what I'd do when I found him.
你查过油箱吗？
Did you check the tank?
是的
Yeah.
我乘海军巡逻艇  沿着岸边而行
I was being ferried down the coast in a navy PBR...
这是种橡皮巡逻艇
a type of plastic patrol boat--
在河上随处可见
a pretty common sight on the rivers.
他们说用来搜集情报
They said it was a good way to pick up information and move...
不会引人注目  这样不错
without drawing a lot of attention, and that was okay.
反正我需要新鲜空气和时间
I needed the air and the time.
唯一的问题是  我并非独自一人
Only problem was I wouldn't be alone.
早安  上尉
Mornin', Captain.
船员绝大多数是新手
The crew were mostly just kids--
爱唱摇滚乐  不知大难临头
rockand rollers with one foot in their graves.
-你多大？  -17
-How old are you?  -Seventeen.
叫大厨的机械师
The machinist--the one they called Chef--
来自新奥尔良
was from New Orleans.
他太紧张  不该来越南
He was wrapped too tight for Vietnam.
或许去新奥尔良也如此
Probably wrapped too tight for New Orleans.
兰斯  开50口径机枪  是洛杉矶南部海滩
Lance, on the forward fifties...
一位著名的冲浪高手
was a famous surfer from the beaches south of L.A.
看他一眼
To look at him,
就知他这辈子没开过枪
you wouldn't believe he'd ever fired a weapon in his life.
克林先生  出身纽约南布朗克斯贫民区
Clean--Mr. Clean--was from some South Bronx shit-hole...
我想越南的阳光和环境
and I think the light and the space of Vietnam...
的确令他清醒不少
really put the zap on his head.
还有  酋长  菲腊
Then there was Phillips, the chief.
这也许是我的任务
It might have been my mission,
但船却由菲腊掌控
but it sure as shit was the chief''s boat.
有两处的水深够
There's about two points where we can draw enough water...
可进入湄南河
to get into the Nung River.
但都很危险  是越共的地盘
They're both hot. Belong to Charlie.
别担心
Don't worry about it.
别抽烟
Don't smoke.
我在这参加过几次特别行动
You know, I've pulled a few special ops in here.
大约半年前
About six months ago...
我带一个人穿过都朗桥
I took a man who was going up past the bridge at Do Lung.
他也是正规军
He was regular army too.
听说他已吞枪自尽
Heard he shot himself in the head.
起初  我认为他们给错了档案
At first I thought they handed me the wrong dossier.
真不敢相信  他们想取这人的性命
I couldn't believe they wanted this man dead.
三代均出身西点  尖子生
Third-generation West Point, top of his class.
韩战  空降兵  获勋章无数
korea, Airborne, about a thousand decorations.
诸如此类的
Et cetera, et cetera.
我听到带子上他的声音  很感兴趣
I'd heard his voice on the tape, and it really put the hookin me...
但无法把它和这人联系起来
but I couldn't connect up that voice with this man.
正如他们所说  他战功卓著
Like they said, he had an impressive career.
或许太卓越了
Maybe too impressive.
简直是完美
I mean, perfect.
他曾被推荐出任要职
He was being groomed for one of the top slots in the corporation--
将军  参谋长  等等
general, chief of staff, anything.
1964年
In 1 664,
他陪顾问官巡视越南后回国
he returned from a tour with Advisory Command in Vietnam...
似乎开始走下坡
and things started to slip.
他交给参谋长联席会议
His report to the Joint Chiefs of Staff
及约翰逊总统的报告被压
and Lyndon Johnson was restricted.
他们似乎并不欣赏他的见解
Seems they didn't dig what he had to tell them.
此后的几个月  他3次申请
During the next few months, he made three requests for transfer...
转住佐治压州班宁堡接受空降训练
to Airborne training, Fort Benning, Georgia,
最终获批
and was finally accepted.
空降兵？
Airborne?
当时他已38岁
He was 38 years old.
他究竟打的什么主意？
Why the fuck would he do that?
1966年  加入特种部队
1966, joins Special Forces...
重回越南
returns to Vietnam.
那是什么？
Hey, what's that?
-弧光行动  -怎么了？
-Arc light.  -What's up?
-B-52轰炸  -什么？
-B-52 strike.  -Yeah?
-那是什么？  -弧光
-What's that?  -Arc light.
真讨厌  每次听到
I hate that. Every time I hear that,
都没好事
something terrible happens.
越共一点也不在乎
Charlie don't never see 'em or hear 'em, man.
又来了
There they are.
冲击力让人呼吸困难
Concussion will suck the air out of your damn lungs.
有可怕的事要发生
Something terrible is gonna happen.
有烟！
Smoke!
是二次燃烧
Secondary burning.
是休伊直升机  有很多架
Hueys over there. Lots of Hueys.
去看看  酋长
Let's have a look, Chief.
是空中骑兵  九团一队
It was the Air-Cav. First of the Ninth
是他们
That's them.
负责护送我们到湄南河口
our escorts to the mouth of the Nung River.
但他们应该
But they were supposed to be waiting for us
在前方30公里处等啊
another 30 kilometers ahead.
空中机动部队  就是没法安生
Well, Air Mobile. Those boys just couldn't stay put.
快点  下来
Hey, kid, come on. Get down. Come on.
九团一队  以前是支骑兵部队
First of the Ninth was an old cavalry division...
卖了马  换成直升机
that had cashed in its horses for choppers...
专在湄南河一带搜敌
and gone tear-assing around 'Nam looking for the shit.
好几次令越共措手不及
They'd given Charlie a few surprises in their time here.
他们这次突袭
What they were mopping up now
一小时前毫无征兆
hadn't even happened yet an hour ago.
继续跑  我们在拍电视
Just keeping running by. We're for television.
别看镜头  继续  快走
Don't look at the camera. Just keep--Go on. keep going.
在拍电视  别看镜头
This is for television. Don't look at the camera.
作战斗状  前进
Just go by like you're fiIghting, like you're fiIghting.
别看镜头  在拍电视
Don't look at the camera. It's for television.Just go through.
快走！ 前进
Just go by. keep on going.
别看镜头  走啊
keep going. Don't look at the camera. Go on. keep going.
对了  快走
All right, come on. Go.
对.这边
Right here. Yes. Over here. Over here.
指挥官在哪？
Where can I fiInd the CO?
上校正准备降落！
That's the colonel comin' down!
指挥官在直升机上
The CO's on that chopper.
中尉  沿后面那条约90米远的林木线轰炸
Lieutenant, bomb that tree line back about 1 00 yards!
-给我点呼吸的空间  -是  长官
-Give me some room to breathe!  -Yes, sir!
-死亡扑克  -什么  长官？
Body cards!
-带上死亡扑克  -是  长官
-Bring my body cards!  -Yes, sir!
在找坦克吗？ 有5辆坏的
I'm the Fourth Tank commander. I got fiIve tanks broken down.
你说够了  上尉
We're all right with the tanks. It's all right, Captain.
我是威尔德上尉！
Captain Willard!
我有情报二处的优先文件
I carry priority papers from Com-Sec Intelligence, II Corps.
相信老川已通知你
I understand Nha Trang has briefed you...
支援我的任务
on the requirements of my mission.
什么任务？  老川没消息来
What mission? I haven't heard from Nha Trang.
长官  你的部队应护送我们进湄南河
Sir, your unit is supposed to escort us into the Nung!
-再安排吧  -上校
-We'll see what we can do.  -Colonel!
让开  上尉  我要办正事
But just stay out of my way until this is done, Captain.
看看有些什么人
All right, let's see what we have. Let's see what we have.
黑桃二  黑桃三  方块四
A two of spades, three of spades, four of diamonds...
梅花六  黑桃八
six of clubs, eight of spades.
这些人不配给J
There isn't one worth a jack in the whole bunch.
方块四
Four of diamonds.
-上尉  那是什么？  -死亡牌！
-Hey, Captain, what's that?  -Death cards!
-什么？  -死亡牌
-What?  -Death cards!
-死亡？  -让越共知道是谁干的
-Death?  -Lets Charlie know who did this.
-振作点  小子  -我们不会伤害你
-Cheer up, son.  -We will not hurt or harm you.
-卧倒！ -卧倒！
-Fire in the hole!  -Fire in the hole!
这地方被越共和北越人控制
This is an area that is controlled by the Vietcong and North Vietnamese.
妈的
Jim.
我们来帮你们
We are here to help you.
欢迎你们
We extend a welcome hand...
-快点  都进去了吗？  -愿意重投
-Come on. Everybody in?  -to those who would like to return...
南越政府的人
to the arms of the South Vietnamese government.
进去  快点！
Get in. Hurry up.
-走吧！ -这地方被
-Move it out.  -This is an area that is controlled...
越共和北越人控制
by the Vietcong and North Vietnamese.
嘿！ 怎么了？
Hey! What's this?
怎么回事？
What is this?
这家伙受了重伤  长官
This man's hurt pretty bad, sir.
他用壶盖掩着肚肠
About the only thing that's holding his guts in, sir, is that pot lid.
是吗？ 你要说什么？
Yeah? What do you have to say?
他是可恶的越共
This soldier is dirty VC.
他想喝水  让他喝田里的水吧
He wants water. He can drink paddy water.
滚开！  给我  给我水壶
Get outta here! Give me that canteen.
-他是越共    -任何勇敢作战的人
-He's VC!  -Any man that's brave enough to--
滚开！  我会踹你的屁股！
Get outta here! I'll kick your fuckin' ass!
他杀了我们很多人！
He killed a lot of our people!
任何勇敢作战  置性命于不顾的人
Any man brave enough to fiIght with his guts...
随时都可喝我的水
strapped on him can drink from my canteen.
上校  我想有个水手
Hey, Colonel, I think one of those sailors
是冲浪手兰斯约翰逊
is Lance Johnson, the surfer.
在哪？  这里吗？  你肯定？
Where? Here? You sure?
他来了
Yeah? Here.
去找他
Down there.
重覆  我们统计了死者
Repeat. We have a body count. We have--
你叫什么  水手？
What's your name, sailor?
三等枪手兰斯约翰逊  长官
-Gunner's Mate Third Class Johnson.
三等枪手
Gunner's Mate Third Class
嗨  是冲浪手兰斯约翰逊吗？
Lance Johnson, the surfer?
是的  长官
Yes, sir.
很荣幸见到你  兰斯
It's an honor to meet you.
我钦佩你的板尖冲浪有好几年了
I've admired your nose riding for years.
还有急转
I like your cutback too.
无人能比！
I think you have the best cutback there is.
-谢谢  长官  -不用叫我长官  兰斯
-Thank you, sir.  -You can cut out the ''sir'' crap.
叫我比尔基尔戈  我喜欢右脚在前
I'm Bill kilgore. I'm a goofy foot.
-他跟你一起的？  -是的
-This guy with ya?  -Yeah.
我想给你介绍几个人
I want you to meet some guys.
-迈克  来自圣地压哥  -很远
-This is Mike from San Diego.  -Far out.
钟尼  来自马里布
Johnny from Malibu.
-嗨  钟尼  -冲浪高手
-John, hi. Far out.  -Solid surfers.
这里没人赶得上你
None of us are anywhere near your class though.
过奖了
No way.
我们经常在附近冲浪  兰斯
We do a lot of surfiIng around here.
我希望尽早完成行动
I like to fiInish operations early.
飞去维杜冲浪
Fly down to Yung Tau for the evening glass.
来这后  一直在哪冲浪  兰斯？
Been riding since you got here?
没有  来后没冲过浪
No way. I haven't surfed since I been here.
以主耶稣基督  带来善行
Through Christ, our Lord...
以基督和圣灵
from Whom all good things come...
光明荣耀归全能天父
through Him in the unity of the Holy Spirit.
-阿门  -我们祈祷  对天父怀有信心
All glory and honor is Yours, Almighty Father.
依着救世主的话
Let us bring our iniquities to the Father in the words our Savior gave us.
我们在天上的父
Our Father, Who art in heaven,
愿你的名被尊为圣（《马太福音》6：9）
hallowed be Thy name.
愿你的国降临
Thy kingdom come.
愿你的旨意成就在地上  如同在天上一样
Thy will be done on earth as it is in heaven.
我们每天所需的食物  求你今天赐给我们
Give us this day our daily bread...
好像我们饶恕了
and forgive us our trespasses as we forgive
得罪我们的人
those who trespass against us.
不要让我们陷入试探
Lead us not into temptation,
救我们脱离那恶者
but deliver us from evil.
基尔戈今天很愉快
kilgore had had a pretty good day for himself.
他们享受牛扒  啤酒
They choppered in the T-bones and the beer...
将基地变成沙滩派对
and turned the LZ into a beach party.
他们越想营造家的感觉
The more they tried to make it just like home...
便越怀念家
the more they made everybody miss it.
我要半生的  不是要冻肉
Make my meat rare--rare but not cold.
我猜他不是个差劲的军官
Well, he wasn't a bad officer, I guess.
他爱下属  和他在一起有安全感
He loved his boys, and you felt safe with him.
他有特殊的魅力
He was one of those guys that had that weird light around him.
但在战场上  他会爱惜身体
You just knew he wasn't gonna get so much as a scratch here.
你的任务怎样了  上尉？
What happened to your mission?
老川把你们都忘了吗？
Nha Trang forget all about you?
空降兵
Airborne.
长官
Sir,
我们可经两处进入河道
two places we can get into the river.
-没错  -这两处
-Yeah.  -Here and here.
虽然三角洲很宽阔
It's a pretty wide delta,
但只有这两处我肯定可进入
but these are the only two spots I'm sure of.
你指的这个村庄不敢领教  威尔德
That village you're pointing at is kind of hairy.
-什么意思？  -就是说很危险
-What do you mean ''hairy,'' sir?  -It's hairy.
有重型武器驻守
Got some pretty heavy ordnance.
我不时在那丢几艘侦察艇
I lost a few recon ships in there now and again.
那该死的村子叫什么？
What's the name of that goddamn village?
云东道或云东里
Vin Drin Dop.  Dop or Lop?
越南鬼起的名字都差不多
Damn gook names all sound the same.
迈克  你了解云东道的这里吗？
Mike, you know anything about this point at Vin Drin Dop?
浪头没得说
That's a fantastic peak.
-浪头？  -近2米高的浪
-Peak?  -About six foot.
很少见  左右滑面也很长
It's an outstanding peak. It's got both the long right and left slide...
浪形前所未见  是冲浪胜地
with a bowl section that's unbelievable.It's just tube city.
为什么不早说？  好浪头
Why didn't you tell me that before? A good peak.
这鬼地方  没见过好浪头
There aren't any good peaks in this whole shitty country.
-只有碎浪  -但那真的很危险
-It's all goddamn beach break.  -It's really hairy in there.
麦克唐纳就死在那
That's where we lost McDonald.
我们受了重创  那是越共的据点
They shot the hell out of us there. That's Charlie's point.
长官  我们可在明天黎明出发
Sir, we can go in there tomorrow at dawn.
早晨常有离岸的微风
There's always a good offshore breeze in the morning.
船可能开不进
We may not be able to get the boat in.
河口恐怕吃水太浅
The draft at the mouth of that river may be too shallow.
我们可吊起船
We'll pick your boat up
放在你希望的地方
and put it down like a baby where you want it.
这是空中骑兵九团一队
This is the First of the Ninth, Air-Cav, son.
空中机动部队
Air mobile!
我能自由选择起降点！
I can take that point and hold it as long as I like.
你可以去那条河的任何地方  上尉
You can get anyplace up that river that suits you, young Captain.
哇  近2米的浪头
Hell, a six-foot peak.
好啊  开一架武装直升机回总部
Take a gunship back to the division.
兰斯  跟迈克一起去  让他挑块冲浪板
Lance, go with Mike and let him pick out a board for you.
拿来我那8ˊ6的冲浪板
Bring me my Yater Spoon, the eight-six.
-我不知道  长官  那  -什么事  大兵？
-I don't know, sir  -What is it, soldier?
那很危险  是越共据点
It's hairy in there. It's Charlie's point.
越共不冲浪
Charlie don't surf!
天呀  克林  难以置信！ 看
Hey,Jesus, Clean, you ain't gonna believe this. Look.
他们要吊起船！
Hey, man! They're pickin' up the boat!
你感觉如何  吉米？
How are you feeling,Jimmy?
没得说  长官！
Like a mean motherfucker, sir!
好吧  全速前进
All right, son, let 'er rip.
走吧
Let's go!
我不习惯用轻板
I never have got used to a light board.
从不习惯
I can't get used to one.
-我习惯用重板  -没错  它不好用
-I'm used to a heavy board.  -I know, it's a real drag.
-你用重板还是轻板？  -重板
-You prefer a heavy or light board?  -Heavier.
-真的？  -真的
-Really?  -Yeah!
我以为年轻人爱轻板
I thought all the young guys like lighter boards.
没法站在板尖冲浪
You can't ride the nose on those.
公爵6号  公爵6号
Big Duke Six.Duke Six to Eagle Thrust.
我是神鹰7号  我们已发现目标
This is Eagle Thrust Seven. We've got it spotted.
神鹰  向2-7-0方位飞
Put on heading two-seven-zero.
保持战斗队形
Assume attack formation.
收到  公爵  我们正进入
That's a roger, Big Duke.
我们来了
We're going in.
我们将迎着旭日低飞
Hey, Lance, we'll come in low out of the rising sun.
离目的地约1英里时  会放音乐
About a mile out, we'll put on the music.
-音乐？  -没错  瓦格纳的《女武神》
-Music?  -Yeah, I use Wagner.
吓怕越共  部下都喜欢
Scares the hell out of the slopes. My boys love it.
他们要放音乐了
Hey, they're gonna play music!
你们为什么坐在头盔上？
How come all you guys sit on your helmet?
这样不会炸掉卵蛋
So we don't get our balls blown off.
公爵告诉神鹰  开始心理战
Big Duke Six to Eagle Thrust. Put on psy war op.
开大声点  是罗密欧狐步舞
Make it loud. This is a Romeo Fox Trot.
跳舞吗？
Shall we dance?
是的  长官
Yes, sir!
-来吧  -好啊
-Come on!  -All right. Fire.
发现林木线那有几个人
We got a couple--at that tree line.
我们在猛轰
We're taking fire from the holes.
跑啊  越共！
Run, Charlie!
这会让一切都烧起来
This should make everything burn.
前面有几个人
We got a couple of people ahead here.
下面怎么了？
What's going down here?
有机关枪  炸了它！
We got an automatic! Shoot to kill!
炸了它！
Shoot to kill in the open!
发现下面有重武器
I spotted a large weapon down below.
我们要去看看
We're gonna go down and check it out.
好的  这是狐步舞  我们要到了
All right, this is Fox Trot. We're pullin'in.
射得好！
What a shot.
没得说  红组
Outstanding, Red Team. Outstanding.
奖一箱啤酒
Get you a case of beer for that.
6-4-1-0  我们在村庄上空
Six-four-one-zero, we're over the village right now.
我看见院里有辆车  我要去看看
I see a vehicle in the courtyard. I'm gonna check it out.
很好  飞鹰  做得好
Well done, Hawks.
沿林木线扫射
Want some twenty-Mike-Mike-Vulcan along those tree lines.
轰掉他们
Ripple the shit out of'em.
桥上有辆车  配有50口径机枪
Got a vehicle on the bridge, 50 caliber on board.
他正过桥  想再次补充弹药
He's moving across to resupply the weapon.
公爵6号  作好掩护  我亲自出马
Big Duke Six, clear the area. I'm coming down myself.
这些人从不认输吗？
Don't these people ever give up?
射得好  基尔戈！
Nice shot, Bill.
-妈的  -没事
-Shit!  -All right, all right!
只是颗照明弹！
It's just a flare! It's a flare!
-让我出去！  -别这样讲
-Gotta get outta here!  -Un-ass that shit.
把它弄出去！
Get it outta here!
把它弄出去  别紧张  只是颗照明弹
Get it out. It's just a flare. It's all right.
大家都好吧？  兰斯  你没事吧？
Everybody all right? Lance?
没事！
I'm fiIne!
趴下！
Get down!
我不去！ 我不去！
I'm not going! I'm not going!
我不去！
I'm not going.
第二波进入广场
We just got a secondary down there in the plaza.
蓝3  蓝4  坚守岗位
Hold on to your position.
公爵6号  这里有人受伤
Duke Six, we've got wounded down there.
抬担架来！
Get a stretcher over here!
天呀！ 救我！
-Please, God! Help me!
-给他注射吗啡！  -天哪！
-Give him some morphine.  -My God! Oh!
0-3-7-7-4-2
Seven-four-two!
医疗直升机呢？
Where's that duster?
我要伤兵在15分钟内送到医院
I want my wounded out of there and in the hospital in 1 5 minutes.
我要我的人撤出
I want my men out.
留人掩护公爵号
Somebody stay in there tight with Big Duke.
这是10-10  我们准备降落
This is Ten-Ten. We're gonna be in,
抬他们进来  然后离开
throw 'em on and get out.
她有手榴弹！
She's got a grenade!
天哪  那东西被炸飞了
The whole thing blew up.
-她引爆了  -他妈的野蛮人
-She blew the shit  -Fucking savages.
找架救伤直升机
Get a medevac.
天哪  她是个笨蛋  我要打死她
Holy Christ, she's a SAP.I'm gonna get that dinkbitch.
去那边  钟尼  射准点
Get over there, Johnny. Roll that right skid right up her ass.
我们必须炸掉些树
We gotta get some air in these trees.
真烦和下面的敌人纠缠
It's goddamn eat-up with enemy down here.
直升机着火  多处被击中
I'm taking fire. I'm taking hits all over.
3点钟方向！ 3点钟方向
Three o'clock! I'm drawing heavy fiIre!
我身陷火中  大火
I'm hit! Mayday! Mayday!
我被击中了！  救命！  尾部旋翼松脱  还能控制
I'm goin'in.My tail rotor's out. I got control.
-觉得怎样？  -惊心动魄
-What do you think?  -Wow! This is really exciting, man.
不  我是说浪！
No! No! The waves!
-浪头！  -噢  是的
-The waves!  -Oh, right.
看  涌向两个方向
Look at that. Breaks both ways.
看
Watch.
瞧！  近2米高的大浪
Watch.Look! Good six-foot swells!
过来  兰斯
Come here, Lance.
小心！
Incoming!
这个着陆点仍很危险
This LZ is still pretty hot, sir.
去别处冲浪吧
Maybe you ought to surf somewhere else.
你懂冲浪吗？   少校？
What do you know about surfiIng, Major?
你从他妈的新泽西来
You're from goddamn New Jersey.
过来！
Come here! Come here!
-换衣服  -现在吗  长官？
-Change!  -You mean right now, sir?
我要试试浪头  换衣服
I wanna see how rideable that stuff is. Go change.
这里仍很危险
It's still pretty hairy out there.
-你想冲浪吗  大兵？  -想  长官
-Do you wanna surf, soldier?  -Yes, sir.
很好  不冲浪  便打仗
That's good, son, 'cause you either surf or fiIght.
明白了？
That clear?
走吧
Get going.
我来掩护他们  替兰斯拿块冲浪板
I'll cover for 'em.And bring a board for Lance.
船不到  什么也没有
We can't do shit until the boat gets here.
兰斯  我打赌你一定迫不及待
Lance, I'll bet you can't wait to get out there.
-什么？  -看见浪涌向两边了吗？
-What?  -See how they break both ways?
在同一时间可一人向左  一人向右
One guy can break right, one left, simultaneous.
你认为如何？
What do you think?
我们还是等涨潮吧
We ought to wait for the tide to come up.
-兰斯  过来  看！  -小心！
-Come here. Look.  -Incoming!
6小时后才涨潮！
The tide doesn't come in for six hours!
你想在这等6小时？
You wanna wait here for six hours?
酋长！
Yo! Chief! Chief!
好了  各位  别躲了
Okay, fellas, quit hiding.
来吧！ 去冲浪
Come on! Let's go!
该死！
Goddamn it!
你不认为休假来冲浪有点冒险吗！
Don't you think it's a little risky for R and R?
上尉  我说在这片海滩冲浪安全
If I say it's safe to surf this beach,
它就安全！
it's safe to surf this beach!
我不怕在这冲浪
I'm not afraid to surf this place!
我要在这鬼地方冲浪
I'll surf this fuckin' place.
给我通话器  大兵
Give me that R-T, soldier.
鸽子4号  这是公爵6号  妈的！
Dove Four, this is Big Duke Six. Goddamn it!
我要你们沿林木线轰炸！
I want that tree line bombed!
公爵6号  收到  鸽子1至3号  准备
Big Duke Six, roger. Dove One-Three, stand by.
炸他们个片甲不留！
Blow them into the Stone Age, son!
-尽快！ 完毕  -不  回去！
-Out!  -No, back, no!
好了  让我处理吧
Let me take care of this.
把它拿开！
Get that out of here!
-对不起  -过来  好的
-I'm sorry.  -Come here now. All right.
退后  不  太太  抱歉！
No, ma'am. Sorry!
吉米！
Jimmy!
飞鹰1  2号  鸽子1至3号
Hawk One-Two, Dove One-Three.
他们要用凝固汽油弹沿林木线轰炸
They need some napalm in the tree line.
能办到吗？
Can you put it down there?
好的  1至3号  我们准备投弹
Right, One-Three. We're fixin' to fuck with 'em.
目标？
What's the target?
遏止林木线附近的迫击炮火
We're trying to suppress some mortar fire off the tree line down there.
收到  我们来了
Roger. Here we come.
好的  全力进攻
Good. Give it all you got.Bring in all your ships.
用我的直升机  送他去医院
Put him in my chopper. Get him back to the hospital.
-不  不  你要和他一道  -快！ 走吧！
-No, no, no, you got to go with him.  -Come on! Go!
走吧！ 告诉我的人  我要我的冲浪板！
Get it outta here!Tell my guys I want my board!
公爵6号  战机已上路
Big Duke Six, this is Dove One-Three.The jets are inbound now.
你还有30秒
You got about 30 seconds to bomb station.
撤回所有人  并做好掩护
Get your people backand heads down.
轰炸会很猛烈
This is gonna be a big one.
别担心
Don't worry.
这地方很快会清理好  别担心
We'll have this place cleaned up in a jiffy, son. Don't you worry.
给我短裤
Give me those shorts.
这是空中骑兵的  我们送给你当礼物
These are from the Air-Cav, a present from me and the boys.
我想看你穿上它冲浪  行吗？
I want to see you do your stuff in 'em out there.
你闻到了吗？
You smell that?
-你闻到了吗？  -什么？
-Do you smell that?  -What?
凝固汽油弹
Napalm, son.
气味独一无二
Nothing else in the world smells like that.
快点  前进！
Come on. Move it! Move it! Move it!
我喜欢凝固汽油弹  在清晨的味道
I love the smell of napalm in the morning.
有一次  我们连续12小时炸一座山头
You know, one time we had a hill bombed for 1 2 hours.
炸完后  我爬上山
When it was all over, I walked up.
一具越共的腐臭尸体  也没发现
We didn't fiInd one of them, not one stinking dink body.
但那汽油味
But the smell--You know, that gasoline smell.
整座山都飘散着
The whole hill smelled like...
胜利的气味
victory.
这仗终有一天会结束
Someday this war's gonna end.
兰斯  有风！
Lance! The wind!
-有风！ -什么？
-The wind!  -What?
它在吹向岸边！
It's blowin' onshore!
吹向这里来
It's gonna blow this place out.
-会破坏浪  -不爽！
-It's gonna ruin it!  -Not cool!
-它要吹散浪头！  -是该死的凝固汽油弹
-It's gonna blow out!  -It's the goddamn napalm!
-就是它引起的  -我知道
-That's what's doin' it! -I know.
真对不起  上校  恐怕你说得对
I'm really sorry, Colonel. I'm afraid that does it.
他名气大
The kid's got a reputation.
别指望他在泥水里冲浪
You can't expect him to surf those sloppy waves.
-我懂  -我是个艺术家  基尔戈
-I understand.  -I'm an artist, Bill.
不能在泥水里冲浪
I couldn't surf that stuff.
瞧  兰斯  我道歉  但不是我的错
I apologize. It's not my fault.
海浪被凝固汽油弹吹散
The waves are gettin' blown out by the napalm.
别怪我
Don't get me wrong--
爆炸的气浪引起了漩涡
It was the bombs causing a vortex with the wind.
我接受你的道歉
I accept your apology.
如果你能再等20分钟
But if you could hang around 20 minutes--
-下次吧  基尔戈  -就20分钟
-Some other time, Bill. -Just 20 minutes!
-我是个艺术家  -别停！
-I'm an artist.  -keep walking.
好吧  试试
Okay, give it a try, guys.
一人向左  一人向右
One goes left and one goes right.
看  兰斯
Look, Lance.
-你想冲浪吗？  -是的！
-You through surfiIng?  -Yeah!
-想对上校说再见吗？  -不
-Wanna say good-bye to the colonel?  -No.
-你肯定？  -肯定！
-You sure?  -Yeah!
-快他妈离开  -只是该死的凝固汽油弹！
-Get the fuck outta here.  -It's the napalm.
就等20分钟！
Just wait 20 minutes!
妈的！ 操！
Damn! Fuck!
他们一直在找你
They've been lookin' for ya.
-别丢下我  -你到底要去哪？
-Don't leave without me!  -Where the fuck you goin'?
小心！
Here!
那是上校的冲浪板！
That's the colonel's surfboard!
离远点  它是我的
Incoming!Hey, get the fuck off me! It's mine!
-兰斯  -大厨  点一只
-Lance.  -Chef, light up, man.
来吧  松弛一下
Come on. Let's get high.
-抽烟吗？  -来吧  点一支
-Wanna smoke?  -Let's do it, man. Light up.
这仗终有一天会结束
Someday this war's gonna end.
对船上的小子们是好事
That would bejust fine with the boys on the boat.
他们只想回家
They weren't looking for anything more than a way home.
-上尉？  -问题是  我回来了
-Captain?  -Trouble is, I'd been back there...
执行不记录在案的任务
and I knew that it just didn't exist anymore.
好正点！
Buddha time. Here.
好啊  真不错  混蛋
All right, that's great, you motherfuckers. Yeah.
若基尔戈这样打仗
If that's how kilgore fought the war...
我开始奇怪他们究竟  和库尔兹有什么不同
I began to wonder what they really had against kurtz.
不仅仅是发疯和谋杀
It wasn't just insanity and murder.
这里所有人都如此
There was enough of that to go around for everyone.
他从不为婊子伤心
I mean, he never was hurtin' for pussy.
我不在这  我正在林中摘芒果
I'm not here. I'm walking through the jungle gathering mangos.
遇到了明星维歌莉
I meet Raquel Welch.
我做了个不错的芒果奶油布丁
I make a nice mango cream pudding.
用它涂满全身
You know, kind of spread it around on us.
她也涂了一身
She's into mangos too.
她爬到我身上
She's like one limb above me.
-我们俩赤裸裸躺在林中  -嗨  酋长
-We're both in the jungle here nude. -Hey, Chief.
-什么？  -那个上校又来了
-Yeah?  -Here comes that colonel guy again.
找到块中意的冲浪板很难
You know how hard it is to find a board you like.
我不会伤害你们
I will not hurt or harm you.
只要把冲浪板还我  兰斯
Just give me back the board, Lance.
这是块好板  我喜欢
It was a good board, and I like it.
找到块中意的冲浪板很难
You know how hard it is to find a board you like.
他真是个顽固的混蛋！
He's a determined motherfucker!
我不会伤害你们
I will not hurt or harm you.
只要把冲浪板还我  兰斯
Just give me back the board, Lance.
这是块好板  我喜欢
It was a good board, and I like it.
找到块中意的冲浪板很难
You know how hard it is to find a board you like.
-我不会伤害你们  -天哪
-I will not hurt or harm you. -Jesus Christ.
这人真他妈烦
That guy's too fuckin' much, man.
他会射我们吗？
Do you think he would have shot us?
他不会在海滩上下手
He wouldn't have shot us on the beach...
但要是看见我拿着他的冲浪板  就会动手的
but he would have shot us if he saw me taking his board.
我们去冲浪吧  大家都学会了
Let's go surfin'now Everybody's learnin'how
-拿开冲浪板！ -傻瓜
-Let's get this board out of my turret.  -Sucker.
下次他再来  我就射他  如何？
How am I going to shoot him the next time he comes around?
大厨  给冲浪板腾块地方
Hey, Chef, make some room back there for the board.
狠狠打我呀  兰斯
Sock it to me, Lance.
不知道是不是同一架直升机
I wonder if that's the same chopper.
他可能让人带着录音  遍布河上
He's probably got them all over the river with that recording.
我们要等到天黑  酋长
We'll have to hold up here till dark, Chief.
别担心  兰斯  他不会跟太远
Don't worry, Lance. He won't follow us too far.
为什么这么说？
What makes you say that?
你以为上校会让上游的人都知道
You think that big Cav colonel wants everyone upriver...
-我们偷了他的冲浪板？  -我没偷
－to know we stole his board?  －I didn't steal it!
上尉
Captain?
还要航行多远？
Just how far up this river we goin'?
是机密  酋长  不能告诉你
It's classifiIed, Chief. I can't tell ya.
我们还远着呢
We're goin' up pretty far.
会有危险吗？
Is it gonna be hairy?
我不知道
I don't know, kid.
也许吧
Yeah, probably.
你喜欢深入虎穴吧  上尉？
You like it like that, Captain, when it's hot, hairy?
妈的
Fuck.
没机会知道
Maybe you'll get a chance to know
你在俄亥俄的工厂里是干嘛的
what the fuck you are in some factory in Ohio.
酋长  我想上岸摘芒果  行吗？
Hey, Chief, I'm gonna go get those mangos now, okay?
-找个人陪你  -我会带着他
-Take somebody with ya.  -Yeah, I'll take--
我会跟他去
I'll go with him.
大厨？
Chef?
-什么  长官？  -他们为什么这样叫你？
-Yes, sir?  -How come they call you that?
-叫我什么  长官？  -大厨
-Call me what, sir?  -Chef.
因为你喜欢芒果之类的吗？
Because you like mangos and stuff?
不  长官  我真是大厨
No, sir, I'm a real chef.
-我是个  酱汁师    -酱汁师？
-I'm a saucier.  -Saucier?
没错  长官
Yes, sir. See,
瞧  我来自新奥尔良
I come from New Orleans.
自小就被培养  要做个伟大的酱汁师
I was raised to be a saucier, a great saucier.
-什么是酱汁师？  -我们专攻酱汁
-What's a saucier?  -You specialize in sauces.
附近一定有芒果树
Gotta be a mango tree here somewhere.
我本来应去巴黎
Then, I was supposed to go to Paris...
入读厨艺学校
study at the EscoffiIer school.
却接到体检通知单
But then I got orders for my physical.
我加入海军
Hell, I joined the navy.
听说吃得较好
Heard they had better food.
还有厨子学校
Cook school--that did it.
-怎么样？  -你不想听的
-Yeah, how's that?  -You don't wanna hear about that.
近百米的上等肉排列在面前
They lined us up in front of a hundred yards of prime rib.
所有人列队看着
All of us, you know, lined up lookin' at it.
肉质极佳  切割很好
MagnifiIcent meat. Really! Beautifully marbled.
接着  他们把肉扔进大锅
Next thing, they're throwing the meat into these big cauldrons--
一锅熟
all of it--boiling it!
我看着肉色变灰
I looked inside, man. It was turning gray.
真他妈不敢相信
I couldn't fucking believe that one.
于是我申请入无线电技师学校
That's when I applied for radioman school,
他们却给了我
but then they gave me--
那是什么？
What is it?
越共？
Charlie?
是老虎！  狗娘养的！
It's a tiger!Son of a bitch!
老虎！ 是老虎！
It's a tiger, man! It's a tiger!
各就各位  兰斯  准备
Battle stations. Lance, up front.
-M60机枪戒备  克林  -收到
-Get on your 60!  -Got it.
天呀！ 大厨  快走！
Holy shit! Chef, come on!
他妈的老虎！
A fuckin' tiger!
上尉  快来！
Captain, come on!
快走！
Let's go!
队长  你说得对！ 永不要下船
You were right. Never get out of the boat.
克林  开动M60机枪？
Bring that 60 forward!
永不要下船！ 我要记住！
I gotta remember! Never get out of the boat!
永不要下船！
Never get out of the boat!
出什么事了？  有多少人？
What happen? How many is it?
-他妈的老虎！  -老虎？
-A fuckin' tiger!  -What? A tiger?
我受够了！
Yes! I've had it!
我是无胆鬼
I've had the whole goddamn fuckin' shit, man!
我想回家
You can kiss my ass on the county square...
我不想留下来
because I'm fuckin' buggin' out.
我加入海军  不是为了送死
I don't fuckin' need it! I don't want it.
我只想做厨师
All I wanted to do was fuckin' cook!
我只想学烹饪
I just wanted to learn to fuckin' cook, man!
没事了
You're all right.
没事了  没事了
You're all right. You're gonna be all right.
不要下船  永不下船
Never get out of the fuckin' boat.
再见  老虎！
Hi, tiger! Bye, tiger! Good-bye!
永不下船
Never get out of the boat.
真是至理名言
Absolutely, goddamn right...
除非你不打算回头
unless you were going all the way.
古华特下了船
kurtz got off the boat.
他离经叛道
He split from the whole fuckin'program.
为什么会这样？
How did that happen?
他第一次来时  遇见什么？
What did he see here that first tour?
那时他已38岁
Thirty-eight fucking years old.
若加入特种部队
If you joined the Green Berets...
晋升至上校已是极限
there was no way you'd ever get above colonel.
古华特知道他要放弃什么
kurtz knew what he was giving up.
我对他认识越多
The more I read and began to understand...
越发敬佩他
the more I admired him.
他的家人  朋友  也不了解他
His family and friends couldn't understand it...
他们无法说服他
and they couldn't talk him out of it.
他申请了三次
He had to apply three times,
承受折磨
and he put up with a ton of shit.
当他以辞职要胁  他们屈服了
But when he threatened to resign, they gave it to him.
班上的后生仔  比他年轻一半
The next youngest guy in his class was half his age.
他们必定认为这老人家
They must have thought he was some far-out old man...
无法完成课程
humping it over that course.
我16岁入读  几乎要了我的命
I did it when I was 1 6. It damn near wasted me.
他真有种
A tough motherfucker.
完成了课程
He finished it.
他不能晋升将军
He could have gone for general...
但选择了自己道路
but he went for himself instead.
亲爱的伊娃：今天很特别
Dear Eva...Today was really a new one.
差点被老虎生吞
Almost got eaten alive by a fuckin' tiger.
真的难以想像
Really un-fucking believable, you know?
我们要带伟利上尉  逆流而上
We're taking this guy, Captain Willard, up the river...
但他不肯讲出目的地
but he hasn't told us yet where we're taking him.
或许你现在已知道
Thought you might have heard by now from Elwood.
1967年10月
October 1 667.
在康通县一次特别任务
On special assignment kontoom Province, II Corps.
古华特与本地军一起执行
kurtz staged Operation Archangel with combined local forces.
取得重大胜利
Rated a major success.
他没有请示上级
He received no official clearance.
只是想到要做  便做了
He just thought it up and did it.
有勇气
What balls.
他们本打算惩罚他
They were gonna nail his ass to the floorboards for that one.
但事件被新闻界揭露
But after the press got ahold of it...
反而晋升他为上校
they promoted him to full colonel instead.
噢
Oh, man,
越南充满谎言和怪诞
the bullshit piled up so fast in Vietnam.
要抽离很不容易
You needed wings to stay above it.
在丛林中  这很不寻常
This sure enough is a bizarre sight in the middle of this shit.
在等我们？
Expecting us this time?
鬼才知道
Damned if I know.
天呀！
Jesus--
-它缩回卡车里了  -什么？
-It goes back up into the truck.  -What?
我们必须让它们立起来
We gotta get all that stuff up.
贺符  你来过这里吗  大厨？
Hau Phat. You ever been up here before, Chef?
我打赌这可以买毒品
I bet you we can score up here.
看看那些单车  兰斯
Check out the bikes, Lance.
雅马哈  铃木
Yamaha, Suzuki. Yeah!
-真不错  -对  棒极了
-That's a good one.  -Yeah, Sukiyaki.
没错  真不赖
Yeah, man. This is something.
-求你  -一定是他
-Please!  -This must be the guy.
在那里
Right over there.
军士
Sergeant.
3桶柴油
Three drums of diesel fuel, PBR fiIve--
快点  走开  我们没时间了
Come on, man! Move!We don't have time.
只有1小时  你要什么？
One hour. That's all. What do you want?
-能给我点巴拿马红色大麻吗？  -没问题
-Can I get some Panama Red?  -Yeah, I'll get you Panama Red.
-军士？  -目的地？
-Sergeant?  -Destination?
我没有目的地
I don't have no destination.
没有目的地  不可买东西
I can't do a goddamn thing without a destination.
-军士？  -有目的地吗？
-Sarge? Sarge?  -I need a destination!
我要目的地  否则办不到
I can't do a thing about it with a destination.
军士  他们跟我一起的  目的地保密
These guys are with me. Destination's classifiIed.
我有情报部门的优先文件
I carry priority papers from Com-Sec Intelligence.
好的  长官  听着  今晚有大行动
Okay, right, sir. Hey, listen, it's a real big night.
-8块  -嘿
-Eight bucks for that  -Hey!
好吧  妈的
All right. Damn.
-给他些燃料  -没问题
-Just give him some fuel.  -You got it.
-狗开始叫了  -听着  上尉
-Dog starts barking.  -Hey, listen, Captain.
今晚实在抱歉
I'm really sorry about tonight.
这儿确实一团糟
It's really bad around here.
拿这给配给处的人支领
Just take this over to the man at the supply desk and you got it.
你们要表演票吗？  记者席的？
Would you guys like some seats--some press box seats for the show?
要吗？  表演就在那边
The show out here.
-是兔女郎  -花花公子兔女郎？
-Bunnies, bunnies.  -Playboy bunnies?
没错  去吗？
You got it. You gonna be here?
听着  上尉  公家出钱
Hey, listen, Captain, on the house.
算是赔罪
No hard feelings, huh?
你们好吗？
How ya doin'out there?
我说你们好吗？
I said, how ya doin'out there?
我们都想向你们问好
Wanna say hello to you from all of us up here...
在  强力攻击  行动中
to all of you out there who work...
真他妈卖命的人
so goddamn hard in Operation Brute Force!
嗨  所有的伞兵！
Hello, all you paratroopers out there!
海军陆战队！ 还有水手们！
And the marines! And the sailors!
我们以你们为荣
We wanna let you know that we're proud of you!
我们知道你们确实辛苦
We know how tough and how hard it's been.
为此  我们送上娱乐节目
To prove it we're gonna give you entertainment
我们知道你们会喜欢的
you're gonna like.
八月小姐贝珊迪
Miss August, Miss Sandra Beatty.
五月小姐泰达莉！
Miss May, Miss Terri Teray! Yeah!
还有年度花花公子玩伴
And the playmate of the year,
科嘉丽小姐！
Miss Carrie Foster! Yeah!
-嗨！ -怎么了？
-Come on!  -What's the matter?
来擦我的枪！
Grease my gun!
我准备好狂欢了  宝贝！
I'm ready to powwow, baby!
你很可爱  我喜欢
You're cute. I like you.
我在这  宝贝！
I'm here, baby! I'm here!
耶！
Yeah!
-你这臭婊子  -脱啊！
-You fucking bitch!  -Take it off!
快脱！
Take it off!
女郎  要我们上来吗？
Hey, lover! You want us to come over!
-最好啦！ -签我的插画！
-I sure do!  -Sign my centerfold!
签我的插画！
Sign my centerfold!
快点  宝贝！ 过来
Come on, baby!
让开！ 快！
Start her up. Hey!
快点
Get out of my way!
求你签  好吗？
Will you sign these? Come on!
女孩们  走了！
Let's go!
快点！ 赶紧！
Let's go!Hurry!
再见
So long!
越共没有劳军晚会
Charlie didn't get much USO.
他们要么死守阵地  要么飞速移动
He was dug in too deep or moving too fast.
他们所想的休假享受
His idea of great R and R
就是冷饭和一点鼠肉
was cold rice and a little rat meat.
他们只有两条路：
He had only two ways home--
战死或胜利
death or victory.
难怪库尔兹激怒上级
No wonder kurtz put a weed up Command's ass.
战争由无能的四星小丑们指挥
The war was being run by a bunch of four-star clowns...
我们注定战败
who were gonna end up giving the whole circus away.
这次机会真难得
Hey, you know, man, that was far-fucking-out.
自她当上十二月小姐
I collected every picture of her
我便收集她的每张照片
since she was Miss December, Chief.
克林  看！ 这有她！
Hey, Clean, look at that. She was here, man.
我还给这骚货写过信
I even wrote to the cunt.
但没有回音
She didn't write me back.
很多人也爱上了这些骚货
You can really get hung up on these broads, man...
就像那只  三角洲  的猫
just like that cat in the delta.
-你最好相信  -什么猫？
-Yeah, you better believe it.  -What cat?
一个军士
The one that went up for murder.
被控谋杀
He was an army sergeant.
记得吗？  他沉迷于  花花公子
Remember? This cat, man--He really dug his Playboy, man.
-我是说  像这个人
-I mean like this guy
每有新书到达
When the thing arrived,
必定早在那等着
he was there to meet it, man.
瞧这漂亮的乳房！
Look at these beautiful fuckin' jugs, man!
他在南越陆军巡逻队工作
Yeah, so anyway, he was workin' ARVN patrols.
有个自大的混账越南中尉
One of them cocky gook asshole lieutenants and shit
一天  越南人拿走他的杂志
One day the gook took his magazine
不肯交还
and wouldn't give it back.
他说   还给我杂志
He said, ''Give me my magazine back.''
那越南鬼说  闭嘴
Gook say, ''You shut up.
我已把你告上了军事法庭
I have you court-martialed.''
-典型的南越军人  -没错
-Typical fuckin' ARVN.  -Yeah!
随后  那越南人开始过分了
Then the gook starts to go too far.
大厨  来开船
Chef. Take the wheel.
这家伙开始在相片的乳房上乱捅
This dude started to stick pinholes in the lady's tits.
他开始戳洞  并撕插画
He started sticking pinholes and mutilating the centerfold.
军士说  你最好别那样对她
The sergeant said, ''You better not do that to her.
拿开你那双脏爪
You leave your shitty little gook hands off of that girl.
别那样对她
Don't do her like that.''
-越南人用越南语说  操你妈的  -该死
-Gook say ''Fuck you'' in Vietnamese.  -Damn.
军士忍无可忍
The sergeant couldn't handle it no more.
他拿起枪
He just picked up his iron...
拉开保险
flipped it to rock and roll and--
一个长连射穿过《花花公子》
Gave that little zero a long burst straight through the Playboy mag.
把越南人轰了个稀巴烂
It blew his ass clean off of the dock.
中尉当场死掉
There wasn't no more lieutenant that day.
就是这样
That was it for his ass.
-他们因此毁了他？  -那军士？ 是的
-They burn him for it?  -The sergeant? Yeah, man.
被控谋杀
They stuck his ass in the LBJ.
没给他块勋章什么的  真是太糟了
It's too bad he didn't get no medals or nothin'.
可恶的南越兵
Fuckin' ARVN, man.
他们早该宰了这混蛋
They should have killed the fuck.
真该给这家伙一枚银星勋章
Should have given the fucker a Silver Star.
越南人都是无赖  对吧？
Bummer for the gook though, ain't it?
早安  越南
Good morning, Vietnam.
我是陆军广播员赞克约翰逊
I'm Army Specialist ZackJohnson on AMVN.
西贡市区现在约28度
It's about 82 degrees in downtown Saigon right now,
非常潮湿
also very humid.
西贡市长有重要消息给所有
We have an important message for all GI's...
驻扎的美国士兵
who are living off base from the mayor of Saigon.
他希望你们把衣物挂在室内
He'd like you to hang your laundry up indoors
而不是晾在窗台上
instead of on the windowsills.
市长希望西贡保持美观
The mayor wants you to keep Saigon beautiful.
现在  播放一首经典老歌
Now here's another blast from the past going out
给大山姆  他正独自和
to Big Sam who's all alone out there
第35步兵团第一营一起  在安溪的火力小队
with the 1 st Battalion, 35th Infantry...
也要献给他们英俊的指挥官
and dedicated by the fire team to their groovy CO.
-滚石乐队的《（我无法得到）满足》  -好啊！
-The Rolling Stones, ''Satisfaction. '' -All right!
当心  克林！
Watch out, Clean!
下来！
Get down, bubba!
坚持住  兰斯！
Hang on, Lance!
下来！
Get down, bubba!
告诉他们你做到了  兰斯
Tell 'em you did it, Lance.
好啊！
All right!
当心  兰斯！
Look out, Lance!
《献身与平叛》
Commitment and Counterinsurgency...
沃特E.库尔兹上校著
by cononel Walt E.kurtz
只要我们的军官和队伍
As long as our officers and troops perform...
都是来逛一年的
tours of duty limited to one year...
他们就会一直是外行
they will remain dilettantes in war and tourists in Vietnam.
只要冰啤酒  热菜  摇滚乐
As long as cold beer, hot food, rockand roll...
和其他一切开心事照旧
and all the other amenities remain the expected norm...
我们的指挥就只会虚弱无力
our conduct of the war will gain only impotence.
我们要精锐部队
We need fewer men, and better.
如果他们肯献身
If they were committed, this war could be won...
用现有军队的  四分之一也可取胜
with a fourth of our present force. ''
妈的  害怕了
Shit. Chicken time.
别胡说  兄弟  那该死的
You ain't shittin', bro. They're motherfuckin'.
-那是谁？  -怎么了？
-Who is that?  －What's going on?
是你吗  拉扎洛？
Is that you, Lazzaro?
帐顶着火了！
Fire on the canopy!
我知道！ 我知道！ 让开！
I got it! Get outta there!
我知道！ 我知道！
Yeah! I got it! I got it! I got it!
兰斯  下去！
Lance, get down!
把那东西拿出来！
Put that fucker out, man!
他们到底以为自己在干什么？
What the fuck they think they're doin'?
1968年夏末秋初
Late summer, autumn 1 668.
库尔兹在高地的巡逻队
kurtz's patrols in the highlands
频繁遭伏击
coming under frequent ambush.
营地开始瓦解
The camp started falling apart.
11月
November.
库尔兹命令
kurtz orders assassination of
暗杀越南的3男1女
three Vietnamese men and one woman.
其中两个男的是南越军上校
Two of the men were colonels in the South Vietnamese army.
敌军在他老防区的活动逐渐停止
Enemy activity in his old sector dropped off to nothing.
估计这四人他杀对了
Guess he must have hit the right four people.
他加入了特种部队
Hejoined the Special Forces.
之后  他的
After that his--
军方尽了最后的努力  想他重回正轨
The army tried one last time to bring him backinto the fold.
方法
methods
若他改过  一切既往不咎
If he'd pulled over it all would have been forgotten.
反常
unsound.
但他一意孤行
But he kept going.
他现在进了柬埔寨
Now he's crossed into Cambodia
而且不断赢得胜利
He kept winning it his way.
和他的这支越南山民军一道
with this Montagnard army of his
这时  上级要我出马
And they called me in.
他们奉他若神明
Man like a god and follow every order,
连极荒谬的命令也执行
however ridiculous.
军方失去了他
They lost him.
他消失了
He was gone.
只有谣言或零星情报传出
Nothing but rumors and random intelligence...
主要来自被俘的越共
mostly from captured VC.
越共都知他大名  全惧怕他
The VC knew his name by now, and they were scared of him.
他带领部下打游击战
He and his men were playing hit-and-run
并转战到柬埔寨
all the way into Cambodia.
我知道我要去哪
I know what I'm doin'.
我要去白宫
I'm goin' to the White House to have dinner...
和总统共进午餐  宝贝
with the president of the United States.
我就要去那
That's where I'm goin'.
大厨  盖上盖
Hey, Chef, put the cover on that.
克林
Clean.
他在船上多久了？
How long has that kid been on this boat?
7个月
Seven months.
他真是会惹我生气
He's really specializing in busting my balls.
很可能  上尉  他也有同感
Very possible, Captain, he thinks the same of you.
是吗？  你有何高见  酋长？
Oh, yeah? What do you think, Chief?
我没想法
I don't think.
上级不让我知道
My orders say I'm not supposed to know
要开船去哪  所以我没想法
where I'm taking this boat so I don't!
但一见你  不管是哪
But one look at you, and I know it's gonna be hot,
就知会有危险
wherever it is.
我们去上游
We're going upriver
距都朗桥约75公里
about 7 5 clicks above the Do Lung Bridge.
那里是柬埔寨  上尉
That's Cambodia, Captain.
是机密任务
That's classifiIed.
我们不该进柬埔寨
We're not supposed to be in Cambodia,
但那就是我要去的地方
but that's where I'm going.
你只管靠近我的目的地
You just get me close to my destination
然后你和船员们便可离开
and I'll cut you and the crew loose.
好吧  上尉
All right, Captain.
亲爱的儿子
''Dear Son...
你和你母亲在过去的几星期
I'm afraid that both you and your mother
没我的消息
will have been worried...
恐怕担心坏了
at not hearing from me during the past weeks...
但我的处境变得艰难了
but my situation here has become a difficult one.
我正式被军方控以谋杀
I have been officially accused of murder by the army.
所谓的受害人
The alleged victims
是4名越南双面间谍
were four Vietnamese double agents.
我们花了数月搜集证据
We spent months uncovering them
好揭穿他们
and accumulating evidence.
当铁证如山时  我们便行动了
When absolute proof was completed, we acted--
像军人一样果敢
we acted like soldiers.
指控是不公正的
The charges are unjustified.
实际上  他们在这种混乱局面下
They are, in fact, and in the circumstances of this conflict...
已完全失去理智
quite completely insane.
在战争中
In a war,
许多时刻要宽容怜悯
there are many moments for compassion and tender action.
还有许多时刻要冷酷无情
There are many moments for ruthless action--
通常所谓的  冷酷无情
what is often called ruthless...
在许多情况下  或许只是头脑清晰
but may in many circumstances be only clarity--
看清了要做什么  并果断行动
seeing clearly what there is to be done and doing it--''
-派救伤直升机来  完毕  -直接
-Medevac, come in.  -''directly--
迅速  清醒
quickly, awake.
阿尔法  探戈  探戈
Alpha, Tango, Tango,
-回话  探戈  阿尔法  -看哪
-Echo, Tango, Alpha.  -Looking at it.
请求救伤直升机  有3  4个人阵亡了  完毕
Request dust-off.Three, maybe four kIA 's. Over.
对这封信
I trust you
我相信你能有选择的告诉你母亲
tell your mother what you choose about this letter.
至于对我的指控  我不在乎
As for the charges against me, I am unconcerned.
派救伤直升机来
Medevac, come in.
我看不起他们懦弱  虚伪的道德观
I am beyond their timid, lying morality,
所以心中再无牵挂
and so I am beyond caring.
救伤直升机  收到了吗？  完毕
Medevac, do you read?  Over.
我完全信任你
You have all my faith.
爱你的父亲
Your loving father.
天哪！
Jesus.
难怪我和他们无线电联络不上
No wonder I couldn't get 'em on the radio.
好一片废墟！
What a dump.
-你好！ -你怎样？
-Hi there!  -How ya doin'?
小船不错
That's a nice little boat you got there.
以前从没船来
Never seen one up here before.
我们叫过救援直升机
We called in a request for Medevac.
你们收到了吗？
You receive it?
救援直升机？  没见
Medevac? No.
倒是经过一架坠毁的休伊直升机  里面有阵亡者
We passed a downed Huey with some kIA's.
-在你们来这的路上？  -是的
-On your way here?  -Yeah.
-那你们要去上游喽？  -是的
-You goin' up this river?  -Way up.
去上游？ 算了吧
Way upriver? Forget it.
为什么？
Why?
我们想送几个人去下游
We want to send some people downriver.
-别去了  -究竟怎么回事？
-Just forget it.  -What the fuck was that?
我们几天后回来
We'll be back in a couple of days.
没错  你们会回来
Yeah, right, you'll be back.
-酋长？  -什么事  上尉？
-Chief?  -Yeah, Captain?
你看看引擎吧
Why don't you see what you can do with that engine?
-我要去四下瞧瞧  -好的
-I'm gonna look around.  -All right.
别丢下我
Hey, don't leave without me.
大兵  你的指挥官呢？
Hey, soldier, where's your CO?
别问我
Don't ask me, man.
还我的衣服  混蛋！
Give my clothes back, you asshole!
该死的混蛋！
Asshole!
指挥官在哪？
Hey, guys, where's the CO?
他两个月前踩中地雷
He stepped on a land mine about two months ago.
完蛋了
He got blown to hell.
-这里谁管事？  -管事？
-Who's in charge here?  -Charge?
不知道  我只管巡夜
I don't know, man. I'm just the night man.
听命而为  妈的
Just do what I'm told. Shit.
我只是个打工妹
I'm just a working girl.
你呢？
What about you, fella?
兰斯  机枪卡住了
Hey, Lance, man, I'm telling you it's gonna jam.
你记住
You mark my words.
-就让它这样吧  它是你的鸡巴  -别找我麻烦
-keep it in that condition  -Get off my back!
-不  我告诉你  -住手！
-No, man, I'm telling you  -Lay off!
嗨！ 过来
Hey! Hey! Come here!
是你的船吗？ 进来吧
Is that your boat? Come on inside.
你想怎样？
What do you want?
进来  我想跟你谈谈  快点！
Come on inside. I want to talk to you. Come on!
躲躲雨
Get out of the rain.
松手
Get off me!
行了  别打了  嗨  酋长  停手
ome on. Cut this shit. Hey, Chef. Hey, come on.
你怎样  上尉？
Hey, how ya doin', Captain?
我想让你见几个人
I want you to meet some people.
-我拿到你的鸡巴了  -你的鸡巴真烂
-I got your ass.  -Your ass is shit.
大厨  你的鸡巴真烂！
Chef, your ass is shit!
你这混蛋
You're a motherfucker, man.
妈的  我的耳朵  你这混蛋
Goddamn, my ear, you motherfucker!
-把他拉开  大厨  -你这自以为是的家伙
-Get him off me, Chef.  -You smart-ass.
嗨  各位
Hey, guys.
我逮住你了！
I got you! I got your ass!
-你不是混蛋  大厨  -嗨  兄弟们
-You ain't shit, Chef.  -Hey, fellas.
-你撞坏了我的膝盖  -嗨  各位
-You pulled my fuckin' -Hey, guys.
我刚和贺符的人做了笔交易
I just made a deal with the people from Hau Phat.
用两桶燃料换取
I negotiated two barrels of fuel
和兔女郎相处几小时
for a couple of hours with the bunnies.
嗨！ 你在逗我吗？
Hey! Hey! You shittin' me?
是真的
No, I'm not.
拿两桶燃料去那个大帐篷
Grab a couple of barrels and get up to that big tent.
快点！
Come on!
上尉
Captain.
你要用我们的燃料
You're giving away our fuel
去换个当月的花花公子玩伴？
for a playmate of the month?
不  是年度玩伴  酋长
Nope, playmate of the year, Chief.
给他们暖暖身子  宝贝！
Warm 'em up, baby!
让他们暖暖
Warm 'em up!
上尉  我们可能会打仗时没燃料
Captain, we get in a fiIre fiIght and run out of fuel...
我要你告诉我她怎么样
I want you to tell me how she was.
我这是为了大家  酋长  你呢？
I made a deal for all of us, Chief. How about you?
-你捞了什么好处？  -什么？
-You got some mamas in there?  -Some what?
算啦  上尉  我留在船上
Forget it, Captain. I'll stay with the boat.
上尉！ 帮把手
Hey, Captain! Give me a hand.
我有
You know, I got a--
我收集了你所有的照片
I got every one of your pictures.
我有插画  玩伴评论
I got the centerfold, the playmate's review...
年度玩伴决赛
the playmate of the year runoff.
甚至还有日历
I even got the calendar.
啊  小鸟  你怎么弄到的？
Hey, oiseau. How come you got a bird?
我以前在布希公园当雀女郎
I used to be the bird girl at Busch Gardens.
-布希公园？  -是的  训练小鸟
-Busch Gardens?  -I used to train birds there.
你是
You are--
-十二月小姐吧？  -五月小姐
-You are Miss December, aren't you?  -Miss May.
松了吗？
Is it coming?
-十二月小姐是黑发  -在那边
-Miss December has black hair.  -It's over there.
它不是我训练的那些小鸟
He's not one of my regular birds.
来吧  宝贝  吃块饼干
Come on. Come on, baby. Snack?
吃块饼干  过来
Snatch a crack. Come here.
当上年度玩伴
Being playmate of the year...
是我能想到的最孤独的经历
is the loneliest experience I can imagine.
就象你想
It's like--You try to express...
向人表达情感  坦露心事
your feelings to someone and show them your heart--
我想听你的驯鸟表演
Yeah, I want to hear about your bird act.
我喜欢听你的驯鸟表演
I'd love to hear about your bird act.
但你不介意戴上这吧？
But would you mind just puttin' this--
为我戴上这黑色假发  成吗？
Would you just mind putting this black wig on for me, please?
而中间却多了道玻璃墙
And there's this glass wall between you--
看不见的玻璃
this invisible glass.
他们能看见你嘴在动
They can see your mouth moving.
我训练小鸟至少有两年了
I used to train birds for at least two years--
-真美  -在布希公园
-That's beautiful.  -at Busch Gardens.
头发散落右肩
This was cascading over your right shoulder.
这里张开
This was open here.
他们却听不见你所说的
But they can't hear what you're saying.
我训练它们倒立  倒转飞
I used to train them to stand on their head
骑小单车
and ride a bicycle--
-你右手有点  -嗨  大厨！
-Your right hand was--  -Hey, Chef!
-滚开！ -快  大厨！
-Get outta here, man!  -Come on!
有人想和你谈谈
Does he want to talk to you?
等会  给我15分钟
Later. Give me 1 5 minutes.
因为你压根没法让他们
You can never really make them hear
听见你要说的
what you're trying to say.
弯弯腰可以吗？  就是这样
You okay with kind of bending? That's it.
你的屁股有点翘  嘿  滚开！
Your ass was sticking out just a little--Hey, man, fuck off!
15分钟！
Fifteen minutes!
所以我拼命要
That's why I tried so desperately...
证明我有才能
to show somebody that I had some talent.
小金刚鹦鹉
Little baby macaws.
-你见过吗？  -就这样打开
-Have you ever seen a baby macaw?  -That's kind of open there.
-它们都是蓝色和金色的  -来  脱掉吧！
-They're all blue-- -Take off, would you?
我有权利！
I got my rights, man!
他们逼你做你不想做的事
They make you do things you don't wanna do--
就象
like,
这张照片
this picture here.
我开始讨厌自己
I started feeling repulsed with myself.
你往前弯点  你的屁股有点翘
You were just kind of bending forward. Your ass kind of out a bit.
我喜欢训练小鸟
I love training birds.
就这样  很好  就这样
That's it. That's very--That's it. Voila.
你真漂亮  我只想
You're beautiful. I just want to--
真不敢相信
You know, I can't believe it.
我  杰伊希克斯
Me,J. Hicks. I can't believe
真的在这
I'm really here.
或许我不配和
Maybe I'm unfiIt to have a relationship...
帅气  纯真的少年发生关系
with a beautiful, innocent boy.
试想想  如果不是越战
Just think, if it hadn't been for the Vietnam War...
我永远不会遇见你  十二月小姐
I never would have met you, Miss December.
五月小姐
Miss May.
我希望    能找到
I wish--I wish I could fiInd...
那么个人
just one person...
他能分享我的感受
that could share my point of view.
你接吻象只小鸟！
Oh, you kiss like a bird!
噢！ 吻我！ 吻我！
Oh, God! kiss me! kiss me!
谁啊？
Who is that?
你让我发疯！ 吻我！
You're drivin' me crazy! kiss me!
我喜欢小鸟！
I love birds!
你搞完没？
You fiInished yet?
妈的！
Oh! Fuck!
象只小鸟！ 象小鸟般歌唱！
Like a bird! Take me like a bird!
飞吧  宝贝！ 你做什么？
Fly, baby! Cock it to me!
-飞吧！  -我能像只鹰般飞翔！
-Fly!  -I can fly like an eagle!
-我是只鹰！  -真让我疯狂！
-Fly like an eagle!  -It drives me crazy!
让我疯狂！
It drives me crazy!
兰斯  死者也有父母
Lance, that was somebody's son.
兰斯  他们逼我做
Lance, there were things that they made me do...
我不愿做的事
that I didn't want to do.
比如  他们说  在双腿间拉丝带
They said, ''Pull the ribbons between your legs.''
我不愿意
I didn't want to do it.
但他们说我该这样
But they said that was what was expected of me...
因为人们喜欢看
that that's what people wanted to see.
-你是谁？  -我是下一个  女士
-Who are you?  -Well, I'm next, ma'am.
该死  我不知道他还是处男
Ha, ha! Hell, I didn't know it was a cherry.
-从没干过女人  -滚开  混蛋
-Didn't know you never got no pussy. -Shove it, fuckup.
抱歉  要早知道
Sorry about that. If I'd have known,
我会带你去新奥尔良的
I'd take you to New Orleans.
-去你的  -教你几招
-Man, fuck you.  -Introduce you to--
-闭嘴  大厨  -憨直处男
-Lay off, Chef.  -Cherry boy, cherry boy.
你这该死的废物！
You're a fuckin' dog!
去新奥尔良吧
Come to New Orleans.
我会帮你找个伴  笨蛋
I'll get you fiIxed up, ya prick.
闭嘴  大厨
Lay off, Chef.
你是这里唯一的笨蛋
You're the only fuckin' prick I see around here.
如果我想找个笨蛋玩  我会找自己的
If I wanna play with a prick, I'll play with my own.
你不知道该怎么办  憨直处男
What are you gonna do with it, cherry boy?
大厨  我说闭嘴！
Chef, I said lay off!
大厨  够了！ 让他喘口气吧！
Chef, knock it off! Give him a break!
听到了吗？
What do you think I said?
让你的嘴歇歇！
Then give your jaws a rest!
这不是陆军  你是个水手
This ain't the army. You are a sailor!
丢了那顶皱巴巴的陆军帽
So get out of that frizzly army-looking shirt...
也别吸大麻了  听到没？
and stop smoking that dope!You hear me?
兰斯  为什么把自己涂绿？
Lance, what's with all the green paint?
-保护色  -干什么？
-Camouflage.  -How's that?
好让敌人看不见我  他们无所不在  大厨
So they can't see ya. They're everywhere, Chief.
我要你保持清醒  你有工作要做
I want you to stay awake up there, man. You got a job to do.
左舷有只舢板  左舷有只舢板
Sampan off the port bow. Sampan off the port bow.
检查一下  蓝斯
Let's take a look,Lance.
拉他们过来  克林
Bring them in. Clean,
上60口径  大厨  准备16口径
on the 60. Chef, get a 1 6.
克林  上60口径！
Clean, get on that 60!
什么事  酋长？
What's up, Chief?
有只舢板  上尉  要做例行检查
Ajunk boat, Captain. We're gonna take a routine check.
算了吧  放他们走
Well, let's forget routine now and let 'em go.
这些船在三角洲运送补给  上尉
These boats are running supplies in this delta, Captain.
我要检查一下
I'm gonna take a look.
酋长  我的任务优先
My mission's got priority.
妈的  如果不是我
You wouldn't even be in this part of the river
你根本到不了这
if it wasn't for me.
只有到了目的地
Until we reach your destination,
上尉  才轮到你发话
Captain, you're just on for the ride.
-准备  兰斯  -快抛绳子  混蛋
-Stand by, Lance.  -Come on. Throw the rope, asshole.
好了  把舢板拉过来
All right. Come on. Let's bring it over.
搜前面的暗格
Look in that forward hooch.
把人带开
Bring the people out of there.
快点！ 混蛋！ 快走！
Come on! Hurry up, motherfucker!
明白  酋长
I got you, Chief.
查完了  酋长
It's clear, Chief.
普通渔民  没问题
Okay, that's them. That's them. They're okay.
-上艇搜  -只是艘破渔船
-Board and search it.  -It's just a fuckin' boat.
-没什么  -上艇搜
-There ain't nothin' on it.  -Board it and search it.
只有篮子  鸭和他妈的香蕉
Just some baskets and some ducks, fuckin' bananas.
没别的
Ain't nothin' on it.
-你怎么了？ 搜啊  -有山羊  鱼
-What's wrong? Search it.  -There's the goat and some fiIsh.
-酋长  -和他妈的蔬菜
-Chef!  -Fuckin' vegetables--
-登船！ -什么也没啊！
-Get on that boat!  -There's nothin' on it, man!
-登船！ -好吧！
-Get on it!  -All right!
让开  混蛋！ 妈的！
Move it, asshole! Goddamn it!
几头猪  还有芒果
Just some pigs! Look, mangoes!
-米袋里有什么？  -他妈的米啊
-What's in the rice bag?  -Fuckin' rice!
-看看里面  大厨！ -椰子和他妈的鱼
-Look in there!  -Some fuckin' fiIsh!
更多的椰子  米  又是米
More coconuts. Rice. Here's rice.
-菜篮里有什么？  -滚开！ 快点！
-What's in that vegetable basket?  -Get out of here!
-什么也没有  -箱里有什么？
-There ain't nothin' in here!  -What's in the boxes?
-搜那个锡罐  生锈的那个  -没什么
-Look in that rusty can.  -Nothing!
只有他妈的米！ 没别的
Just fuckin' rice! There ain't nothin' on it!
搜那个黄桶  她正坐在上面  里面有什么？
Check the yellow can! She was sittin' on it. What's in it?
大厨！
Chef!
混蛋！
Motherfuckers!
-住手！ -来吧  把他们都宰了
-Hold it!  -Come on! Let's kill them all.
-舔鸡巴的小丑！  -住手！
-Motherfucking cocksuckers mothers!  -Hold it! Hold it!
把这些混蛋都宰了吧！
Let's kill all the assholes!
屎都给他们打出来！
Shoot the shit outta all of'em.
-住手  大厨！ 住手  -干嘛停手？ 天哪
-Hold it!  -Why not? Jesus Christ.
干嘛停手？
Why the fuck not?
-克林？  -我没事
-Clean?  -I'm good.
-没事吧  兰斯？  -妈的！
-You okay, Lance?  -Shit! Fuck! Shit!
-大厨  你没事吧？  -看她在藏什么？
-Chef!  -Look what she was hiding!
-你没事吧？  -看看她为什么跑？
-You all right?  -See what she was runnin' for?
是只他妈的小狗
It's a fuckin' puppy.
-把小狗给我！ -不！ 不给你！
-Give me that dog!  -No! You're not gonna get it!
-他妈的给我！ -不  给我  混蛋！
-Give it to me!  -Give me the fuckin' dog, asshole!
操你的！
Fuck you!
-大厨  -还有他妈的芒果！ 你想要吗？
-Chef-- -You want that?Fuckin' mango too!
大厨！ 她在你背后动呢  她没死  瞧瞧她
She's moving behind you. She's alive. Check her out.
大厨！ 她在你背后动呢  瞧瞧她
Chef! She's moving behind you. Check her out!
好了  好了
All right. All right.
-来吧  克林！ -她没死  只是伤了
-Come on, Clean! Goddamn it!  -She's not dead. She's wounded.
克林  帮他一把
Give him a hand.
放松
Just take it easy.
-慢点  放松  -好的  大厨  稍等一下
-Slow down and take it easy.  -Chef, wait a minute.
-带她上来  -还有呼吸吗？
-Bring her up.  -Is she breathing?
她受伤流血了
She's hurt. She's bleedin'.
扶她上船  我们送她去南越军
Bring her on board. We're taking her to an ARVN.
你在说什么？
What are you talking about?
我们送她去友军处
We're taking her to some friendlies.
-她受了伤  没死  -走开  大厨
-She's wounded. She's not dead.  -Get out of there.
上尉  条例说
The book says--
去他妈的！
Fuck you. Fuck 'im.
我说过不要停  开船
I told you not to stop. Now let's go.
这就是我们的生活方式
It was a way we had over here of living with ourselves.
我们会用机枪  把他们撕成两半
We'd cut 'em in half with a machine gun
再给他们个邦迪
and give 'em a Band-Aid.
这是个谎言
It was a lie.
我看得越多
And the more I saw of them...
越讨厌谎言
the more I hated lies.
他们看我的眼神
Those boys were never gonna look at me
再不会一样了
the same way again...
但我觉得自己知道一两件
but I felt like I knew one or two things
库尔兹没在档案里的事
about kurtz that weren't in the dossier.
都朗桥是湄南河上最后的据点
Do Lung Bridge was the last army outpost on the Nung River.
再过去  就是库尔兹的地盘
Beyond it, there was only kurtz.
-觉得怎样？  -很漂亮
-What do you think?  -It's beautiful.
你怎么了？  看起来有点怪
What's the matter with you? You're acting kind of weird.
知道我省下的最后一粒迷幻药吗？
Hey, you know that last tab of acid I was saving?
-知道  -我嗑了
-Yeah,I know.  -I dropped it.
-你嗑了迷幻药  -过瘾
-You dropped acid?  -Far out.
嗨  友军！ 友军！
Friendly! Friendly! Friendly!
-带我回家！ -妈的！
-Take me home!  -Goddamn it!
-该死的海岸警  -你想死吗？
-Fucking shore police! Shit!  -Man, you wanna die?
别走！
Don't keep goin'!
-该死的警察！ -别丢下我！
-You fuckin' police!  -Don't leave me!
操你的！
Fuck you!
你们会遭报应的！
You'll get what you deserve!
-威尔德上尉在船上吗？  -在
-Is there a Captain Willard on board?  -Yeah.
-威尔德上尉？  -我就是  你是谁？
-Captain Willard?  -Yeah. Who's that?
-卡尔森上尉  长官  -别照我
-Lieutenant Carlsen, sir.  -Get that light off me!
3天前老川派我来的  长官
I was sent here from Nha Trang with these three days ago, sir.
他们以为你会早点到  有信给船员
Expected you here a little sooner. This is mail for the boat.
你不知道这让我有多开心  长官
Don't know how happy this makes me.
-为什么？  -我可以走了
-Why?  -Now I can get out of here,
如果能找到路的话
if I can fiInd a way.
你在地狱里  上尉
You're in the asshole of the world, Captain.
上尉  你去哪？
Captain, where you going?
看看能不能找到燃料和情报
See if I can fiInd some fuel and get some information.
到桥那边接我
Pick me up at the other side of the bridge.
-陪他去  -大厨
-Somebody go with him.  -Chef.
我去吧
I'll go.
我想去
I wanna go.
听那音乐
Man, listen to the music, man.
指挥官在哪？
Where can I fiInd the CO?
-你就站在他上面  混球  -兰斯！
-You came right to it, son of a bitch!  －Lance.
下来！
Get down here!
你们还有指挥官吗？
You still got a commanding offiIcer here?
-在贝弗利山  -什么？
-Beverly Hills.  -What?
顺着路直上去
Straight up the road,
有个他妈的混凝土掩体
there's a concrete fucking bunker
叫贝弗利山！
called Beverly Hills!
你以为还会是哪？
Where the fuck else do you think it would be?
妈的  你踩到了我的脸
Goddamn it! You stepped in my face.
我们以为你死了
I thought you were dead.
你们想错了  妈的
Well, you thought wrong, damn it!
告诉过你不要惹我的  对吧？
I told you to stop fucking with me, didn't I?
觉得自己很猛吗  黑鬼？
You think you're so bad, huh, nigger?
你在射什么  大兵？
What are you shooting at, soldier?
嘿  你他妈以为我在射什么？
What the fuck ya think I'm shootin' at?
抱歉  长官
I'm sorry, sir.
铁丝网外有越南鬼
There are gooks out there by the wire.
不过  我想我把他们都宰了
But I think I killed them all.
干掉个鬼  你听
You ain't shot shit. Listen.
妈的  他想叫帮手
Oh, shit. He's trying to call his friends.
发射闪光弹
Send up a flare.
觉得自己很猛吗  黑鬼？ 是不是？
Think you so bad, huh, nigger? You think you bad, huh?
他们都死了  蠢货
They're all dead, stupid.
尸体下还有个活人
There's one still alive underneath them bodies.
谁是这里的指挥官？
Who's the commanding offiIcer here?
不是你吗？
Ain't you?
觉得自己很猛吗？
You think you so bad?
去死吧  黑鬼！
I got something for your ass now, nigger!
去死吧！
I got something for you now!
他在尸体下面
He's underneath the bodies, man.
-去找域祖  黑鬼！ -我去找域祖
-Go get the Roach, nigger!  -Go get the Roach for me.
域祖！ 域祖！
Roach. Roach.
域祖！
Roach.
铁丝网旁有越共  听到了吗？
Got slopes on the wire, man. You hear 'em?
-兰斯！ -听到了吗？
-Lance.  -Do you hear 'em?
杀死他们！
We'll bust 'em!
听到了吗
Hear him out there on the wire, man?
是的
Yeah.
我宰了你  美国兵！
I kill you, GI!
要照明弹吗？
You need a flare?
不要
No.
他在附近
He's close, man.
非常近
He's real close.
美国兵  去死吧！
Fuck you, GI! I kill you!
美国兵！ 去死
Fuck you, GI!
笨蛋
Motherfucker.
嗨  大兵
Hey, soldier.
谁是这里的指挥？
Do you know who's in command here?
知道
Yeah.
妈的
Holy shit.
酋长  刚有两个人被炸下桥
Hey, Chief, man. Two guys just got blown off that bridge.
顶住  不会有事的
You hang on, man. You're gonna be okay.
-是什么？  -邮件
-What's that?  -Mail, man. Mail.
迟些再看！ 盯着那些树
Later on the mail. Watch them trees.
没有柴油  但找到了些弹药
There's no diesel fuel, but I picked up some ammo.
走吧
Let's move out.
找到指挥了吗  上尉？
Did you fiInd the CO, Captain?
这里就没他妈的指挥
There's no fucking CO here.
我们继续走吧
Let's just get goin'.
往哪走  上尉？
Which way, Captain?
明知故问  酋长
You know which way, Chief.
你要靠自己了  上尉
You're on your own, Captain.
仍想去上游？ 就像这座桥
Still wanna go on? It's like this bridge.
每晚我们搭起来  越共就将它炸毁
We build it every night, Charlie blows it right back up again...
当官的仍说路通了
just so the generals can say the road's open.
想想吧
Think about it.
-谁在乎？  -带我们去上游！
-Who cares? -Just get us upriver!
大厨  去船头
Chef, on the bow.
-准备  克林  -出发！
-Stand by, Clean.  -Let's go!
这是谁的包裹？
Whose package is that?
-妈的  又是你的  克林  -是吧  等一下
-Shit, you got another one, Clean.  -No shit? Wait a minute.
是它吗？
You got one, Miller. Geez, I got some too.
你的  兰斯
That's it for you. Lance.
约翰逊先生（时任总统）  你的
Mr. L.B.Johnson, there you go.
好啊  正等这个呢
Far out, man. All right. I've been waitin' for this one.
我又收到一个
I got another one.
伊娃寄来的邮包
I got a box from Eva.
兰斯  我很好
''Lance. I'm fiIne. I'm fiIne.
我和雪儿去迪士尼乐园玩了
Sue and I went tripping in Disneyland.
雪儿擦伤了膝盖
Sue skinned her knee.''
我想回新奥尔良的餐厅
Man, I wanna get back to Antoine's.
我记得那时光
''I remember the time we went up to--''
我怎能他妈的忘记？
How could I fucking forget?
太美了
Beautiful.
没有哪比得上迪士尼乐园  要是有
''There could never be a place like Disneyland, or could there?
告诉我
Let me know.''
吉米  它真的在这！
Jim, it's here. It really is here.
你的任务有了新进展
''There has been a new development regarding your mission...
我们必须现在通知你
which we must now communicate to you.
数月前  有人奉命执行
Months ago, a man was ordered
同一任务
on a mission which was identical to yours.
有理由相信
We have reason to believe
他现在投向了库尔兹
that he is now operating with Col. kurtz.
考虑到他家人  西贡将他列入了失踪名单
Saigon was carrying him MIA for his family's sake...
可他们认为他死了
but they assumed he was dead.
后来  他们截获了  他想交给妻子的一封信
Then they intercepted a letter he tried to send to his wife. ''
理查德科比上尉
Captain Richard Colby.
他跟了库尔兹
He was with kurtz.
迪士尼乐园
Disneyland.
妈的  这里比迪士尼乐园好玩
Fuck, man, this is better than Disneyland.
查尔斯M·曼森
''Charles Miller Manson
下令屠杀所有在家的人
ordered the slaughter of all in the home...
以示抗议
anyway as a symbol of protest.''
真是奇怪  对吧？
That's really weird, ain't it?
-看  紫烟！  -兰斯  把烟弄熄
-Purple haze. Look, man.  -Hey, Lance, put away that smoke.
我拿了盘妈妈的录音给酋长
I got a tape from my mom.
缤纷的现实
Rainbow reality, man.
酋长  深吸一口
Hey, Chief, get a good whiff.
伊娃想象不出我在越南的生活
Eva can't picture me in Vietnam.
只能想着我在家  边喝啤酒边看电视的模样
She pictures me at home having a beer watching TV.
-嗨  兰斯  -真烫
-Hey, Lance, man.  -Oh, hot potato, hot potato.
很高兴你决定加入海军
I'm so glad you decided to join the navy.
伊娃不确定  能否和我继续交往
Eva's not sure she can have a relationship with me, you know.
我在他妈的2万公里外
Here I am, 1 3,000 fucking miles away...
尽力想维系一段感情
trying to keep a relationship with my ass.
这比我能对你的朋友  说的多多了
That's much more than I can say for some of your friends.
你要喜欢这带子  我会让爸和家人
If this tape is any good...I will have Dad and the family
-寄一盘他们自己的  -嗨  兰斯
-send you a tape of their own. -Hey,Lance.
那边！ 在那边！
There! Over there!
There. Over there!
大厨！ 看看克林！
Chef, check out Clean!
上尉  克林中枪了
Captain, he's hit. Clean's hit.
-兰斯！ -小狗跑去哪了？
-Lance!   -Where'd the dog go?
兰斯  看看克林
Lance! They got Clean.
小狗呢？ 我们要回头找小狗
Where's the dog? We gotta go back and get the dog.
嗨  克林！
Hey, Clean. Hey.
你不能死  混蛋！
Bubba, you can't die, you fucker!
真希望很快
And so I'm hoping that--pretty soon--
快点  但不要太快
not too soon--but pretty soon
会有许多孙子让我宠爱
I'll have a lot of grandchildren to love and spoil.
当你老婆带他们回来时
And then when your wife get 'em back,
她会欣喜若狂的
she'll be mad with me.
连杰茜姨和妈妈
Even Aunt Jessie and Mama...
也会来庆祝你的归家
will come to celebrate your coming home.
奶奶和爸
Granny and Dad are trying
正设法存够钱给你买辆车
to get enough money to get you a car...
但别告诉他们
but don't tell 'em
因为这是我们之间的秘密
because that's our secret.
无论如何  做正确的事
Anyhow, do the right thing...
避开子弹
stay out of the way of the bullets...
完整无缺的回家
and bring your heinie home all in one piece...
因为我们都很爱你
because we love you very much.
爱你的妈妈
Love, Mom.
克林
Clean.
稍等
Hold on.
把望远镜扔给我
Throw me the glasses.
兰斯  在船头架支16口径
Lance, take a 1 6 on the bow.
大厨  上60口径
Chef. Chef. On the 60.
妈的
Fuck me.
兰斯
Lance.
掩护上尉
Cover the captain.
兰斯  掩护上尉
Cover the captain. Lance.
他们是法国人
They're French. They're French.
大厨  收起武器！ 收起武器！
Pick up that weapon! Pick it up! Pick it up!
别后退  上尉
Stand fast. Captain.
好吧  大家放下武器
All right, you men. Put down your weapons.
我们死了个人
We lost one of our men.
法国人一向  对盟友的死致以敬意
We French always pay respect to the dead of our allies.
欢迎你们
You're all welcome.
我叫赫伯特德马海
My name is Hubert DeMarais.
这是我家的种植园
This is my family's plantation.
有70年了
It has been such for 70 years.
它会一直这样  除非我们都死了
And it will be such until we are all dead.
上尉  请代表一个心怀感激的国家
Captain, accept the flag of Tyrone Miller...
接受蒂龙米勒的旗帜
on behalf of a grateful nation.
食物很美味
This food is really wonderful, isn't it?
好酒  好酱汁
The wine, the sauces.
难以置信
I can't believe it.
我能跟厨师谈谈吗？
Hey, can I speak with the chef?
厨师只讲越南语
The chef speak only Vietnamese.
别逗了厨艺这么好
No kidding? He cooks like this
竟然不会讲法语？
and he can't even speak French?
兰斯  厨师是个越南人
Hey, Lance, the chef's a slope.
兰斯
Lance.
波德莱尔的诗
This is Baudelaire.
对孩子来说太残酷
It's a very cruel poem for children.
但他们需要
But they need it,
因为生活有时很残酷
'cause life sometimes is very cruel.
如你所见
As you can see.
靠家人抵抗攻击
Attack repels by the family.
只为了这场战争
Just for this war.
越共  58个
Vietcong, 58.
北越人  12个
North Vietnamese, 1 2.
南越人  11个
South Vietnamese, 1 1 .
美国人  6个？
Americans, six?
嗯  可能有误
Yes. Well, there were perhaps mistakes.
荣幸介绍威尔德上尉
May I present Captain Willard.
伞兵团的
He is of a paratroop regiment.
-萨嫮勒夫人  -上尉
-Madame Sarrault.  -Captain.
抱歉  上尉  只是个有关
Oh, I'm sorry, Captain. It was just a little story...
战争期间  巴黎和挨饿的人的小故事
about Paris and people starving during the war.
他们围坐在桌旁
They are all around the table,
片刻沉默后  一个人说
and there was a silence and somebody say...
有天使经过
An angel is passing by.''
于是另一个人说  我们吃了她
So somebody said, ''Let's eat it.''
你们大概要留多久？
How long can you possibly stay here?
永远
We stay forever.
不  我是说
No, no. I mean...
你们为什么不回法国的家？
why don't you go back home to France?
回家？
Back home?
这就是我们的家  上尉
I mean, this is our home, Captain.
-迟早  你们会  -不会
－Sooner or later, you're--  －No.
你不懂我们的心理
You don't understand our mentality--
法国军官的心理
the French offiIcer mentality!
首先  我们输了二战
At fiIrst, we lose in Second World War.
我不是说你们美国胜了  但法国输了
I don't say that you Americans win, but we lose.
噢  爸爸
Oh, Papa--
在奠边府  我们败了  在阿尔及利压  我们败了
In Dien Bien Phu, we lose. In Algeria, we lose.
在印度支那  我们败了！
In Indochina, we lose!
但在这里  我们没败！
But here we don't lose!
我们坚守着这片土地
This piece of earth, we keep it.
永远不会失去它  永远！
We will never lose it. Never!
你们美国人
You Americans.
在1945年
In 1 945, yeah...
对日作战后
after the Japanese war,
你们的总统罗斯福
your President Roosevelt
不想让法国人留在印度支那
didn't want the French people to stay in Indochina.
所以你们美国人  安插进越盟（追随胡志明）
So...you Americans implant the Vietminh.
-他什么意思？  -这是真的
-What's he mean?  -Yeah, that's true.
越共由美国人创建
The Vietcong were invented by the Americans.
美国人？
The Americans?
现在  你们取代了法国
And now you take the French place...
于是  越盟打你们
and the Vietminh fiIght you.
你们能怎样？
And what can you do?
束手无策
Nothing.
完全束手无策
Absolutely nothing.
越南人很聪明
The Vietnamese are very intelligent.
你从不知道他们的想法
You never know what they think.
他们找苏联人帮忙
The Russian ones who help them,
说来给我们钱
Come and give us their money.
我们都是共产党  找中国人说
We are all Communists. Chinese,
给我们武器  我们都是兄弟
give us guns. We are all brothers.''
他们讨厌中国人！
They hate the Chinese!
比起苏联人和中国人
Maybe they hate the American
他们也许还不那么讨厌美国人
less than the Russian and the Chinese.
就是说  如果明天越南人成了共产党
I mean, if tomorrow the Vietnamese are Communists...
他们也会是  越南  共产党
they will be Vietnamese Communists.
这点  你们美国人永远不会明白
And this is something that you never understood, you American.
我不知道  或许将来
I don't know.
我们会与越盟和解
Maybe in the future we can make something with the Vietminh.
你不明白吗？
Don't you understand?
越共说  走开  走开
The VC say, ''Go away. Go away.''
所有白人  都无法呆在印度支那
That's fiInish for all the white people in Indochina.
法国人和美国人并无分别
If you're French, American, that's all the same.
走吧  他们想忘掉你们
''Go.'' They want to forget you.
瞧  上尉
Look, Captain.
这是事实
Look,this is the truth.
一只鸡蛋
An egg.
蛋白流走
The white left...
可蛋黄仍在
but the yellow stays!
我在西贡时  跟一个美国政客谈过
When I was in Saigon, I spoke to an American politician.
他解释得很好  他说：
He explained it very well. He said, ''Look.
瞧  昨天是朝鲜  今天是越南
Yesterday, it was korea. Today, Vietnam.
明天是泰国  菲律宾
Tomorrow, Thailand, the Philippines...
之后  可能是欧洲
then maybe Europe.''
为什么不会是欧洲？
Come on. Why not Europe?
看看捷克斯洛伐克  最近发生的
Look what happened in Czechoslovakia recently.
甚至在二战前
Even before Second World War
美国人就知道了  要发生什么事
Americans knew exactly what was going on.
他们不想那混蛋接管
They don't want that shit to take over! LeFevre!
你们白人都是混蛋
All you white people are shit.
他们在为自由抗争
They are fiIghting--fiIghting for freedom.
自由？  胡扯
Freedom? Bullshit.
法国人胡话  美国人胡话
French bullshit. American bullshit.
奠边府的陷阱
Dien Bien Phu, that serious.
所有士兵  都知道他们已经完了
All soldiers know they are already dead.
你知道奠边府战役吗？
You know anything about Dien Bien Phu?
-我知道  -不  你不知道
-Yeah, I know.  -No, you don't.
不真的知道
Not really.
奠边府是个错误  一个军事错误
Dien Bien Phu was an error.A military mistake.
错误？  是个故意的错误！
A mistake? A voluntary mistake!
故意的！
Voluntary!
所有士兵都知道
All the soldiers knew.
我们知道自己会死
We knew we would be dead.
那些将军和上校以为
The generals and the colonels believe it's impossible for the Viets...
越南人不可能运大炮上山
to get the cannon up there in the mountains.
但他们办到了
But they do.
然后等着下雨
Then they wait for the rain to come.
雨下起来后  没有飞机能到那
When it comes, no airplane can fly there.
我们的伞兵  从90米高往下跳下
And our paratroopers jump at 90 meters.
90米  70米
I mean, you know, 90 meters--70 meters.
真是发疯
I mean, that's crazy.
没哪支军队会那样干
No army in the world can do that.
他们只想跟朋友们死在一起
And they only do that to be dead with their friends.
法国军队被牺牲了
The French Army was sacrifiIced.
被安安稳稳在家的政客们牺牲了
SacrifiIced by the politicians safe at home.
他们把军队推入了
They put the army in an impossible situation
不可能取胜的境地
where they couldn't win.
学生们在巴黎游行示威
The students are marching in Paris protesting, demonstrating.
从背后捅了士兵们一刀
They stab the soldiers in their back.
士兵要拉响手雷
The soldier would open the grenade,
它却不会爆炸
it wouldn't work.
一张字条掉了出来
A piece of paper would fall--
法国妇女联盟  我们支持越南
''Union of French Women.'' ''We are for the Viets.''
叛徒！ 国内的共产党叛徒
Traitors! Communist traitors at home.
这就是奠边府
Dien Bien Phu, okay.
法国人是混蛋
The French is shit, huh?
没人关心  没人想要
No one care. No one want--
你们美国人为何
Why don't you Americans learn from us,
不从我们的错误中学乖？
from our mistakes?
依你们的军队  你们的实力
Mon Dieux, with your army, your strength your power,
只要你们想就能赢！
you could win if you want to!
你们能赢
You can win.
我肯定我们能在这有所作为
You know, I'm sure we can make something here.
我肯定
I'm sure about it, you know?
我从不亏待这里的人
I never do something wrong to the people here.
抱歉
That's right,
可国内的共产党从没背叛
but the Communist at home have never been traitors.
晚安  上尉
Capitaine, good night.
他是个社会主义者
He was a Socialist, you know.
我知道我们能留下
I know that we can stay.
我知道我们能留下并开创事业
I know that we can stay.We can.
我们经常帮越南人
You know, we always helped the people.
跟他们一起干活
We work with the people.
所以我们  可以推断自己是受欢迎的
So we can be friends, we are agreed.
瞧  上尉  我的祖父
See, Captain, when my grandfather...
和叔父刚来时
and my uncle's father came here...
这里一片荒芜
there was nothing--nothing.
越南什么也不是
The Vietnamese were nothing.
于是我们非常努力地工作
So we worked hard...
从巴西运来橡胶树
the rubber from Brazil,
种植在这里
and then plant it here.
我们雇用越南人  和他们一起干活
We took the Vietnamese, work with them...
从无到有
make something--something out of nothing.
你问我为何我们想留下  上尉
So when you ask me why we want to stay here, Captain...
我们想留下  因为这地方是我们的
we want to stay here because it's ours
它属于我们  令我们的家人团结
it belongs to us.It keeps our family together.
我们为此而战
I mean, we fiIght for that.
而你们美国人
While you Americans, you are fiIghting for...
却为史上最虚无的东西而战
the biggest nothing in history.
对不起  上尉
I'm sorry, Captain.
我会去看看你们的人
I will see if your men need any help
是否需要东西修船
to repair your boat...
好继续你们的战争
so that you can go on with your war.
我为我的家人向你道歉  上尉
I apologize for my family, Captain.
我们都在这里失去了很多
We have all lost much here.
赫伯特失去了妻子和两个孩子
Hubert--his wife and two sons.
我失去了丈夫
And I have lost a husband.
我明白了
I understand.
你厌倦了战争
You are tired of the war.
我能从你脸上看出来
I can see it in your face.
和法国士兵眼神里的一个样
'Twas the same in the eyes of the soldiers of our war.
我们称他们为
We called them ''Les Soldats Perdus--''
迷失的士兵
The Lost Soldiers.
如果你愿意  我们可以来点科纳克白兰地
If you like, we can have some cognac.
不了
No.I...
我得去找我的部下  而且
I have to--to see about my men and--
明天  这里还会有战争
The war will be still here tomorrow.
是的  我想你是对的
Yeah, I guess you're right.
我注意到你晚餐时没喝酒
I noticed you had no wine at dinner.
我不喝酒
No, I don't drink wine.
我是喜欢科纳克
I do like cognac,
但现在不想喝  谢谢
but I don't want any now. Thank you.
好吧
Well...
我只好一个人喝了
then I--I must drink alone.
你战后会回美国吗？
Will you go back after the war to America?
不会
No.
那你跟我们一样  家就在这
Then you're like us--your home is here.
你知道人为什么
Do you know why you can never step
不能两次踏入同一条河流吗？
into the same river twice?
知道  因为它总在流动
Yeah. 'Cause it's always moving.
我以前常为丈夫准备一管
I used to prepare a pipe for my husband.
他心脏受伤  要靠吗啡止痛
'Twas the morphine he took for the wounds he suffered in his heart.
我那迷失的士兵  会大吵大嚷
He would rage and he would cry, my lost soldier.
我对他说
And I said to him,
你看不到有两个你吗？
There are two of you.Don't you see?
一个杀人  一个爱人
One that kills and one that loves.''
他对我说
And he said to me...
我不晓得自己  是畜生还是神
''I don't know whether I'm an animal or a god.''
但你两者皆是
But you are both.
还要吗？
You want more?
重要的是  你还活着
All that matters is that you're alive.
你还活着  上尉
You are alive, Captain.
这就是真相
That's the truth.
你看不到有两个你吗？
There are two of you, don't you see?
一个杀人  一个爱人
One that kills...and one that loves.
什么也看不见  停下
Can't see nothing. We stoppin'.
你无权停船  酋长
You're not authorized to stop this boat, Chief.
我说了什么也看不见
I said I can't see a thing,
上尉！ 我要停船
Captain. I'm stopping this boat.
我不会再拿任何人冒险
I ain't riskin' no more lives.
这里由我指挥  妈的
I'm in command here, goddamn it.
你要听我的
You'll do what I say.
你看见什么了吗  大厨？
You see anything, Chef?
他们为什么不他妈的攻击？
Why don't they fucking attack, man?
小心这  酋长
Watch it over here, Chief.
有截断树桩
Got a stump.
兰斯  上50口径机枪
Lance,On the fiIfties.
他在附近
He was close.
相当近
He was real close.
我虽然看不见他  但却能感觉到
I couldn't see him yet, but I could feel him...
就像船只被卷入上游
as if the boat were being sucked upriver...
而河水会流回丛林
and the water was flowing backinto thejungle.
无论如何
Whatever was going to happen...
都和他们在老川
it wasn't going to be the way
形容的有天壤之别
they called it backin Nha Trang.
-有箭！  -开火！
-Arrows!  -Fire!
大厨  开火！
Chef, open up! Fire!
Lance, fiIre!
大厨！ 没事了  停火
Chef! Chef, it's okay. Quit fiIring.
只是玩具箭
They're just little toy arrows.
闭嘴！ 安静！
Cut it out! Quiet!
酋长  叫他们停火！
Chief, tell them to hold their fiIre!
不过是小树枝
They're just little sticks.
想吓唬我们
They're just trying to scare us.
安静！
Quiet!
你让我们陷入狼狈
You got us into this mess,
现在却无计可施
and now you can't get us out...
因为你也不知道究竟要去哪  是吧？
You got us into this mess, and now you can't get us out...
是吧？
Do ya?
你这混蛋！
You son of a bitch! You bastard!
兰斯  来开船！
Lance, get the wheel!
你们这些野蛮人  来尝尝吧！ 你这混蛋！
You savages! Come and get it! You son of a bitches!
一支长矛
A spear?
我的任务是进柬埔寨
My mission is to make it up into Cambodia.
在那  有个绿色贝雷帽的上校疯了
There's a Green Beret colonel up there who's gone insane...
我要去处决他
and I'm supposed to kill him.
真有种！
That's fucking typical! Shit!
他妈的越南任务
Fuckin' Vietnam mission!
我们必须去那
I'm short and we gotta go up there
好让你杀个自己人？
so you can kill one of our own guys?
真他妈的好！
That's fucking great!
真他妈的发疯
Shit! That's fuckin' crazy.
我以为你要去炸座桥
I mean, I thought you were going in to blow up a bridge...
或铁路之类的
or some fuckin' railroad tracks or somethin'.
-对不起  -不  等等
-That's all right.  -No. No, wait. Wait.
我们一起坐船去
We'll go together, on the boat. We'll go with you.
一起坐船去  好吗？
We'll go up there, but on the boat. Okay?
我对到那后
Part of me was afraid of what I would find...
会发现和要做的事  有点恐惧
and what I would do when I got there.
我知道有危险
I knew the risks...
或假装自己知道
or imagined I knew.
但比恐惧感觉更强烈的
But the thing I felt the most...much stronger than fear...
是渴望面对他
was the desire to confront him.
继续前进
Just keep movin'.
兰斯  手离枪远点
Lance, keep your hands away from the guns.
没事！ 允许你们进来了！
It's all right! It's all right! It's all been approved!
我才不进去！ 那些混蛋会袭击我们！
I ain't comin' in there! Them bastards attacked us!
用汽笛吓跑他们！
Hey, zap 'em with your siren, man. Zap 'em with your siren.
那有水雷！ 那也有！
There's mines over there and mines over there too.
小心  那些该死的猴子会咬人
And watch out. Those goddamn monkeys will bite you, I'll tell you.
真不错  朝着我开
Ah, that's a pretty one. Move it right in towards me.
我是美国人！ 美国平民
I'm an American.Yeah. An American civilian.
嗨  美国佬
Hi, Yanks.
美国平民  没事了
Hi. American.American civilian. It's all right.
你有我梦寐以求的香烟
And you got the cigarettes. And that's what I've been dreaming about.
大厨
Chelf.
你是谁？
Who are you?
你又是谁？
我是个摄影记者
I'm a photojournalist.
我自64年起  就负责报道这场战争
I've covered the war since '64.
去过老挝  柬埔寨和越南
I've been in Laos, Cambodia and 'Nam.
老实说  这船一团糟
Hoo-wee, baby. I'll tell you one thing. This boat is a mess, man.
这些是什么人？
Who are all these people?
他们认为你是来
Yeah, well, they think you've come to--
带他走的  希望不是这样
to take him away.And I hope that isn't true.
带谁走？
Take who away?
他呀  库上校！
Him! Col. kurtz.
你能看见的  都是他的子民
These are all his children, man, as far as you can see.
这里的人全是他的子民
Hell, man, out here we're all his children.
我们能跟库上校谈谈吗？
Could we talk to Col. kurtz?
你不是跟上校谈
Hey, mac. You don't talk to the colonel.
而是听他说
Well, you listen to him.
他启发我们
The man's enlarged my mind.
在传统意义上  他是个诗人战土
He's a poet warrior in the classic sense.
就是说  有时他    你向他问好
I mean, sometimes he'll--Well, you say hello to him, right?
他会走过你身旁  却对你视若无睹
He'll just walk by you and he won't even notice you.
突然又会抓住你
Then suddenly he'll grab you
带到一个角落  说
and he'll throw you in a corner and he'll say...
你知不知道生命中充满假如？
''Do you know that 'if' is the middle word in 'life'?
假如所有的人都失去理智并指责你
If you can keep your head
而你仍保持清醒
when all about you are losing theirs and blaming you.
假如所有的人都怀疑你  而你仍能相信自己
If you can trust yourself when all men doubt you.''
我不能  我是小人物  他是个伟人
I'm a little man. I'm a little man. He's a great man.
我愿有一对锯齿状的爪
''I should have been a pair of ragged claws...
好划破沉默的海底
scuttling across floors of silent seas.''
-我是说  -留在船上
-I mean--  -Stay with the boat.
别丢下我  好吗？
Don't go any--Don't go without me, okay?
我要拍照
I wanna get a picture.
他有时很可怕  有时很普通
He can be terrible and he can be mean...
他可能是对的
and he can be right.
他在战斗
He's fiIghting the war.
他是个伟人
He's a great man.
我是说
I mean--
我希望能用语言来形容
I wish I had words, you know. I wish I had words.
我可以告诉你  前几天他想杀我
I could tell you something like, the other day he wanted to kill me.
诸如此类
Something like that.
他为什么想杀你？
Why'd he want to kill you?
因为我拍了他的照片
Because I took his picture.
他说  你要是再拍我
He said, ''If you take my picture again...
我就宰了你
I'm gonna kill you.''
他是认真的
And he meant it.
所以你得保持冷静  懂吗？
See, just lay cool. Lay cool.Lay back. Dig it.
他又友善了  确实如此
He gets friendly again. He really does.
但你无法猜度上校
But you don't--you don't--you don't judge the colonel.
你不能用正常人的尺度猜度他
You don't judge the colonel like an ordinary man.
好了  看着  这些是美国人！ 美国人
Okay, watch it now. These are Americans. Americans!
好好感受这个地方
You can feel the vibe of this place.
让我给你拍照
Let me take your picture.
你能停  ？  嗨！ 嗨！
Hey, could you hold--Hey, hello. Hello.
你能停一下吗？
Could you hold up a minute?
科比
Colby.
那些头
The heads.
你在看那些头
You're looking at the heads.
有时他做过了火
I, uh--Sometimes he goes too far.
会第一个站出来承认
He's the fiIrst one to admit it.
-他疯了  -不对！
-He's gone crazy.  -Wrong, wrong!
如果你早到两天
If you could have heard the man just two days ago--
听了他的讲话
if you could have heard him then, God--
-你还会说他疯了？  -绝对是
-You were gonna call him crazy?  -Fuckin' A!
我只想跟他谈谈
I just wanna talk to him.
嗯  他已经走了
Well, man, he's gone away.
他和部下一起
He's gone away.
消失在了丛林中
He disappeared out in the jungle with his people.
我会等他
I'll wait for him.
他和部下在一起  感觉自在
He feels comfortable with his people.
跟他们在一起  他忘了自己
He forgets himself with his people.
他忘了自己
He forgets himself.
上尉？
Captain?
也许我们该回船上等
Maybe we should wait back at the boat.
-我认为你  -好的  大厨
-I think you should-- -Okay, Chef.
我们要回船上一会
We'll go back to the boat for a while.
好的  陪着兰斯
Yeah, stay with Lance.
这上校是个疯子
This colonel guy, he's wacko, man.
比疯掉还糟  他是恶魔
He's worse than crazy. He's evil!
这就是他因之自命不凡的
I mean, that's what the man's got set up here, man!
该死的异教偶像崇拜！ 看看四周
It's fuckin' pagan idolatry. Look around you!
-妈的  他是个疯子  -那你会帮我吗？
-Shit, he's loco.  -Then you'll help me?
帮忙？ 当然  为了从这摊烂事中脱身
Fuckin' A, I'll help you.
我会做任何事
I'll do anything to get out of this joint.
好样的
Good boy.
我们可以把他们都炸上天
We could blow all them assholes away.
他们离得这么远  甚至不会觉察
They're so fuckin' spaced out, they wouldn't even know it.
我不怕他们那些
I ain't afraid of
头骨  祭坛之类的恶心东西
fuckin' skulls and altars and shit.
我一直认为  要是死在邪恶的地方
I used to think if I died in an evil place...
灵魂就无法入天堂
then my soul wouldn't be able to make it to Heaven.
但现在  操
But now, fuck--
我不管它去哪  只要别在这
I mean, I don't care where it goes, as long as it ain't here.
你想怎么办？ 我要杀了那混蛋
So what do you wanna do? I'll kill the fuck.
滚开
Get out of here.
我要你等在这  大厨
I'm gonna need you to wait here, Chef.
我会和兰斯去四周转转
I'll go up with Lance and scrounge around,
查查这地方
check the place out.
看能否找到上校  行吗？
See if I can fiInd the colonel, okay?
你要我做什么？
Well, what do you want me to do?
守着无线电
Here. You take the radio...
若到22时我仍没回来
and if I don't get back by 2200 hours...
你就要求空袭
you call in the air strike.
空袭？
''Air strike?''
密码是  全能
The code is ''Almighty''...
坐标：  0-9-2-6-4-7-1-2
coordinates zero-niner-two-six-four-seven-one-two.
都在这里
It's all in there.
0-9-2-6-4-7-1-2
Zero-niner-two-six-four-seven-one-two.
我所见的都告诉我：  库尔兹已经疯了
Everything I saw told me that kurtz had gone insane.
这里尸骸遍地
The place was full of bodies--
北越人  越共  柬埔寨人
North Vietnamese, Vietcong, Cambodians.
若我还能活着  那是因为他不想我死
If I was still alive, it was because he wanted me that way.
死亡的气息渐渐逼近
It smelled like slow death in there--
疟疾  噩梦
malaria...and nightmares.
这是河的尽头
This was the end of the river, all right.
你从哪来  威尔德？
Where are you from, Willard?
俄亥俄  长官
I'm from Ohio, sir.
你在那出生的？
Were you born there?
是的  长官
Yes, sir.
哪个地区？
Whereabouts?
托莱多  长官
Toledo, sir.
离河有多远？
How far are you from the river?
俄亥俄河吗  长官？
The Ohio River, sir?
2百多公里
About 200 miles.
我小时候到过那河一次
I went down that river once when I was a kid.
河上有个地方    我想不起来了
There's a place in the river--I can't remember--
曾有个栀子园
Must've been a gardenia plantation
或是花园
or a flower plantation at one time.
现在都荒了
It's all wild and overgrown now. But for about--
但有那么8公里长
for about fiIve miles you'd think that...
让你会以为天堂落入凡间
heaven just fell on the earth...
成了栀子园
in the form of gardenias.
你曾考虑过
Have you ever considered...
任何真正的自由吗？
any real freedoms?
不被他人意见左右的自由？
Freedoms from the opinion of others?
甚至不被自己的看法左右？
Even the opinions of yourself?
他们说过为什么  威尔德？
Did they say why, Willard?
为什么想终结我的指挥吗？
Why they wanted to terminate my command?
我的任务保密  长官
I was sent on a classifiIed mission, sir.
不再是秘密了
It's no longer classifiIed,
对吧？
is it?
他们对你说了什么？
What did they tell you?
他们告诉我你已经
They told me...that you had gone...
彻底疯了
totally insane...
你的行为反常
and that your methods were unsound.
我的方式反常吗？
Are my methods unsound?
我没看到任何
I don't see any method...
反常行为  长官
at all, sir.
我料到会有你这样的人来
I expected...someone like you.
你指望什么？
What did you expect?
你是个杀手吗？
Are you an assassin?
我是个战士
I'm a soldier.
你什么也不是
You're neither.
你是杂货店伙计派来
You're an errand boy  sent by grocery clerks...
收账的跑腿
to collect the bill.
为什么？
Why, huh?
为什么像你这样的聪明人  要杀一个天才？
Why would a nice guy like you wanna kill a genius?
觉得很过瘾吗？
Feeling pretty good, huh?
为什么？
Why?
知道吗？
Do you know--
你知不知道
Do you know that the man--
他确实喜欢你？
the man really likes you?
他喜欢你  真的
He likes you. He really likes you.
但他有些心里话要对你说
But he's got something in mind for you.
你不好奇吗？
Aren't you curious about that?
我好奇
I'm curious.
非常好奇
I'm very curious.
你好奇吗？
Are you curious?
这里有事发生
There's something happening out here, man.
你知道  有些事你没我清楚
You know something, man. I know something that you don't know.
没错  杰克
That's right,Jack.
他心里雪亮
The man is clear in his mind...
但灵魂发了疯
but his soul is mad.
没错
Oh, yeah.
我认为他快死了
He's dying, I think.
他讨厌这一切
He hates all this. He hates it.
但他
But the man's--
他大声读诗  对吗？
He reads poetry out loud, all right?
那声音
And a voice--
声音
a voice--
他喜欢你  因为你还活着
He likes you 'cause you're still alive.
他对你做了安排
He's got plans for you.
不  我不会帮你  你要帮他
No, no, I'm not gonna help you.You're gonna help him, man.
你要帮他
You're gonna help him.
我是说  若他死了  他们会怎么说？
I mean, what are they gonna say, man, when he's gone, huh?
因为他和它是生死相连的
'Cause he dies when it dies, man. When it dies, he dies.
他们会怎么说他？
What are they gonna say about him? What are they gonna say?
会说他仁慈？
He was a kind man?
英明？ 他有谋略？ 有智慧？
He was a wise man? He had plans? He had wisdom?
胡扯
Bullshit, man!
我会是那个  让他们醒悟的人吗？
Am I gonna be the one that's gonna set them straight?
看着我  错了！
Look at me. Wrong!
你
You.
快8个小时了
Almost eight hours.
我睡着了
I'm asleep.
我睡着了  梦见在这艘破船上
I'm asleep and dreaming I'm on this shitty boat.
妈的
Fuck.
已经8个小时了吗？
Has it been eight hours?
嗨  全能  全能
Hello. Almighty. Almighty.
我是街霸  通信检查  完毕
This is PBR Street Gang. Radio check. Over.
街霸  全能  已就绪  完毕
PBRStreet Gang, this is Almighty standing by. Over.
妈的！
Oh,Jesus!
天哪！
Oh, Christ!
《时代》杂志
Time magazine.
新闻性周刊
The weekly newsmagazine.
1967年9月22日
September 22, 1 967. Volume 90...
90卷12册
number 1 2.
《地平线上的战斗》
''The War on the Horizon.
美国人民或许很难相信
The American people may fiInd it hard to believe...
美国正在赢得越战
that the US is winning the war in Vietnam.
然而
Nevertheless...
一份对目前战争态势最详尽的
one of the most exhaustive inquiries...
经过整理的调查
into the status of the conflict yet compiled...
提供了足够的证据  表明美国当局
offers considerable evidence that the weight of US power...
在大举进攻后的两年半
two-and-a-half years after the big buildup began...
开始感受到了自身的强大
is beginning to make itself felt.
白宫官员坚称  由此带来的影响
White House offiIcials maintain the impact of that strength...
可能令敌方
may bring the enemy to the point where he could...
无法继续抵抗
simply be unable to continue fiIghting.''
熟悉吧？
Is this familiar?
由于约翰逊总统  担心美国公众
''Because Lyndon Johnson fears that the US public...
无法接受这一乐观结论
is in no mood to accept its optimistic conclusions...
可能不会允许  报告在秋季发布
he may never permit the report to be released in full.
即便如此  他仍对结论印象深刻
Even so, he is suffiIciently impressed with the fiIndings...
并迫切想公开  他们的研究结果
and suffiIciently anxious to make their conclusions known...
以便这方面的专家
to permit experts who have been working on it...
能泛泛的谈论它
to talk about it in general terms.''
没有日期的《时代周刊》
No date, Time magazine.
罗伯特汤普森爵士
''Sir Robert Thompson...
曾在马来半岛  击败共产党游击队
who led the victory over Communist guerillas in Malaya...
他现在是  兰德公司（美军智库）的顾问
is now a RAND corporation consultant...
最近回到越南
recently returned to Vietnam
向尼克松总统报告形势
to sound out the situation for President Nixon.
上周  他告诉总统
He told the president last week...
情况大有好转
that things felt much better...
以后会更好
and smelled much better over there.''
你怎么想  大兵？
How do they smell to you, soldier?
你会自由  会有人看管你
You'll be free. You'll be under guard.
闲暇时读读这些
Read these at your leisure.
别弄丢了
Don't lose them.
别想逃  会打死你
Don't try to escape. You'll be shot.
我们回头可以谈谈这些
We can talk of these things later.
我们是空心人
''We are the hollow men.
我们是稻草人
We are the stuffed men...
依靠在一起  脑壳中装满了稻草
leaning together at peace fiIlled with straw.
我们干巴的嗓音
Alas, our dried voices
当我们在一块儿窃窃低语时
when we whisper together...
寂静又毫无意义
are quiet and meaningless as wind in dry grass...
好似干草地上的风
or a rat's feet over broken glass in a dry cellar.
或我们干燥的地窖中
He's really out there.
他真在那
He is really there.
成形却没有形式
Shape without form...
成影却没有颜色
shade without color...
力量瘫痪
paralyzed force...
有姿势却无动作
gesture without motion.''
你知道他在说什么吗？
Do you know what the man's saying?
知道吗？
Do you?
这是辩证法
This is dialectics.
非常简单的辩证法
It's very simple dialectics.
就像从1到9  没有或许
It's one through nine. No maybes,
没有假设  没有分数
no supposes, no fractions.
你不能在太空漫游
You can't travel in space.
你不能进入太空
You can't go out into space, you know...
要是没有分数的话
without like, you know, with fractions.
你要在哪着陆？  1/4？ 3/8？
What are you gonna land on? One-quarter? Three-eighths?
若从这去金星  你要做什么？
What are you gonna do when you go from here to Venus?
这是辩证物理学  对吗？
That's dialectic physics, okay.
辩证逻辑认为非爱即恨
Dialectic logic is, there's only love and hate.
你要么爱人  要么恨人
You either love somebody or you hate 'em.
蠢货！
Mutt!
你这蠢货
You mutt.
这就是这该死的世界  结束的方式
This is the way the fucking world is.
看看我们这鬼地方
Look at this fucking shit we're in, man!
并非一声巨响  而是一阵呜咽
Not with a bang. A whimper.
伴随这阵呜咽
And with a whimper,
我他妈闪了  杰克
I'm fucking splitting,Jack.
在河上
On the river,
在那一刻  我看着他
I thought that the minute I looked at him...
我会知道要做什么
I'd know what to do.
结果并非如此
But it didn't happen.
我和他在一起好几天
I was in there with him for days.
没有守卫
Not under guard.
我是自由的
I was free.
但他知道我哪也不会去
But he knew I wasn't going anywhere.
我要做什么  他比我还清楚
He knew more about what I was going to do than I did.
若老川的将军们  看见这一情景
If the generals backin Nha Trang could see what I saw...
仍想让我杀了他吗？
would they still want me to kill him?
或许更为急切
More than ever, probably.
若他的家人知道
And what would his people back home want
他已经离他们有多遥远时
if they ever learned...
他们会怎么想？
just how far from them he'd really gone?
他跟他们决裂了
He broke from them...
然后  跟自己也决裂了
and then he broke from himself.
我从没见一个人  被如此的隔绝
I'd never seen a man so broken up and...
和撕裂
ripped apart.
我看见了恐怖
I've seen the horrors--
你见过的恐怖
horrors that you've seen.
你无权称我是凶手
But you have no right to call me a murderer.
你有权杀我
You have a right to kill me.
你有这个权力
You have a right to do that.
但你无权审判我
But you have no right to judge me.
对于那些
It's impossible for words...
不知道什么叫恐怖的人
to describe...
来说
what is necessary
无法用语言
to those
向他们描述
who do not know
什么是必需的
what horror means.
恐怖
Horror.
恐怖有张面孔
Horror has a face.
你必须与之结交
And you must make a friend of horror.
恐怖与道德恐怖
Horror and moral terror...
应是你的朋友
are your friends.
如果不是
If they are not...
那他们便是  你应惧怕的敌人
then they are enemies to be feared.
他们是真正的敌人
They are truly enemies.
我记得在特种部队的日子
I remember when I was with Special Forces.
似乎是千百年前的事了
Seems a thousand centuries ago.
我们进了一个营地
We went into a camp to inoculate...
给一些孩子打预防针
some children.
替他们注射完  预防小儿麻痹的疫苗后
We'd left the camp...
我们离开了营地
after we had inoculated the children for polio.
这个老人
And this old man came running after us,
在我们后面边跑边哭
and he was crying.
他看不见
He couldn't say.
我们回去时
We went back there...
他们已经来过了  砍掉了
and they had come and hacked off...
所有接种过的手臂
every inoculated arm.
它们堆成了一堆
There they were, in a pile--
一堆
a pile of...
小小的手臂
little arms.
我记得
And I remember...
我哭了  像一些老大娘般
I-I--I cried.I wept like...
抹眼泪
some grandmother.
我咬牙切齿
I wanted to tear my teeth out.
不知道自己想干什么
I didn't know what I wanted to do.
我要记着这一幕  永不忘记
And I want to remember it. I never want to forget it.
永不忘记
I never want to forget.
然后我顿悟
And then I realized...
如同中弹
like I was shot--
如同一颗钻石般  坚硬的子弹
like I was shot with a diamond--
正中我的前额
a diamond bullet right through my forehead.
于是我想  天哪  真是天才
And I thought, ''My God, the genius of that.
天才
The genius.''
这么干的决心
The will to do that.
完美  真实 彻底 清晰 纯粹
Perfect, genuine, complete, crystalline, pure.
然后  我明白了
And then I realized...
他们比我强悍  因为他们受得了
they were stronger than me because they could stand it.
这些人并非怪物  他们是人
These were not monsters. These were men--
受过训练的骨干
trained cadres.
他们用心作战
These men who fought with their hearts...
他们有家庭  子女
who have families, who have children...
心中充满了爱
who are fiIlled with love...
但他们有力量
that they had the strength--
有这样做的
the strength...
力量
to do that.
若我有十师的这号人马
If I had ten divisions of those men...
这里的麻烦很快便会摆平
then our troubles here would be over very quickly.
你的部下必须
You have to have men...
有道德观
who are moral...
同时也能
and at the same time...
利用他们的
who are able to...
原始本能去杀人
utilize their primordial instincts to kill...
不带感情  不会激动
without feeling, without passion...
不去判断是非
without judgment--without judgment.
因为正是判断令我们落败
Because it's judgment that defeats us.
我担心我儿子
I worry that my son...
也许不明白我的用意
might not understand what I've tried to be.
若我被杀  威尔德
And if I were to be killed, Willard...
我希望有人去我家
I would want someone to go to my home...
告诉我儿子这一切
and tell my son everything.
我所做的和你看到的一切
Everything I did. Everything you saw.
因为最令我厌恶的
Because there's nothing that I detest more than...
莫过于谎言的恶臭了
the stench of lies.
如果你理解我  威尔德
And if you understand me, Willard, you--
你会为我作这件事的
you will do this for me.
街霸  这是  全能  完毕
PBRStreet Gang, this is Almighty. Over.
街霸    全能  已就绪  完毕
PBRStreet Gang, this is Almighty standing by. Over.
街霸  全能已就绪
PBRStreet Gang, this is Almighty standing by.
听到了吗？
How do you copy?
他们会因此升我为少校
They were gonna make me a major for this...
而我甚至不在  他们的狗屁军队里了
and I wasn't even in their fuckin'army anymore.
人人都希望我下手
Everybody wanted me to do it.
最渴望的是他
Him most of all.
我觉得他似乎就在那
I felt like he was up there...
等着我去解除痛苦
waiting for me to take the pain away.
他只想死得像个军人
He just wanted to go out like a soldier...
站立着
standing up.
不像那些  可怜的  被遗弃的叛徒
Not like some poor, wasted, rag-assed renegade.
连丛林也想让他死
Even the jungle wanted him dead.
而他正是听命于它
And that's who he really took his orders from anyway.
我们训练年轻人轰炸别人
We train young men to drop fiIre on people...
但他们的指挥官
but their commanders...
却不准他们在飞机上
won't allow them to write ''fuck''...
写  操
on their airplanes
因为这
because...
下流！
it's obscene.
恐怖
The horror.
呼叫街霸
Calling PBRStreet Gang.
街霸  我是  全能
PBRStreet Gang, this is Almighty.
听到了吗？ 完毕
Do you read me? Over.
街霸？
PBRStreet Gang?
街霸  我是  全能
PBRStreet Gang, this is Almighty--
恐怖
The horror.